<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The moralitie of the fourth commandement</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04390</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52528857</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178839</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240873511</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2617A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180685</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">52528857</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04390)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178839)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2772:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The moralitie of the fourth commandement</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>119 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>165-?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, torn, blurred print with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Ten commandments --  Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178839:1"/>
            <p>THE MORALITIE Of the Fourth COMMANDEMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2. God Rested the Seventh Day from all his Works, <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.4.</bibl>
            </p>
            <q>Observa Diem Sabbati, non carnaliter, non Judaicis deliciis, qui otio abutuntur ad nequitiam. Melius enim utique totô die fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derent, quam toto die saltarent: sed tu co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitans requiem in Deo tuo, abstine ab opere servili. <bibl>
                  <hi>August. in Psal. 32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:178839:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:178839:2"/>
            <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
            <p>TRuth, though most Ancient, and in it selfe most plain; yet to the World Credulous of Error, blind, as to Truth, soon imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and long holding the one, soon forsaking, and easily offended at the other: It appears a meer <hi>Novelty,</hi> Acts 17.18.19.20. as those Waters seemed Blood to the <hi>Moabites eyes,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.22. Long Custome,<note place="margin">Cosuetado tempore cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborata pro lege habetur <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi>
               </note> and old Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, strengthened with the Wit and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Men, doth so farre prevaile, as to give credit and authority to Error, to be generally received for Truth; and the tenure, that most hold their practises in religion by, is not so much Scripture, the Rule and Guide of Conscience, as Custome and Example; so as Custome is oft turned into, and Pleaded for as Conscience. We should not wonder at the prejudices Men take at Truth; the greatest Professors of it, have sometimes been the greatest opposers, and most ignorant of it. Who Studied the <hi>Messias</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:178839:3"/> more in Prophesies, seemed more to long for <hi>his</hi> comming, then the Learned Scribes and Pharisees, with the High Priests and Rabbines? Yet when he comes, they despise him, see no forme nor beauty in him; account him a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver of the People; one possest with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; Hate him, Persecute him, Crucifie him, Imbrue their Hearts and Hands in his Blood: One would have thought, of all others, they had been most unlike to have acted that Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Certain <hi>Devout Persons,</hi> Acts 13.50. were the greatest Enemies to <hi>Paul:</hi> The greatest Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders formerly to Church-Discipline and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, were the greatest Enemies to it. Had holy <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> lived in our dayes, 'its possible they would have had as high thoughts of the wayes of the Churches of <hi>Christ,</hi> as any we can wish to our Godly Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Brethren. If God with-hold his Light from Shining out, the Brightest Starre in the Church will become darke; the highest Starre Shines but with a borrowed Light; and that should humble us, and make us thankfull, not to be exalted with any abundance of Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; If God hath made it <hi>Goshen</hi> with us in our understandings, be farre from insulting and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178839:3"/> boasting over our fellow Brethren who differ from us. God denies discoveries of Truth often to very eminent Saints, for high and glorious ends best known to himselfe. Experience tells us, That to every Age God hath deseigned some distinguishing Truth, to try the Obedience, Love and Patience of his Saints, and for the world to stumble at. We are now upon the border of the most glorious times, for discovery of Truth, and for the pouring out of the Spirit: we had need have our Eyes about us, and be circumspect and watchfull against rejecting Truth, as well as imbracing Error; that Satan invents such va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of Errors in these dayes, it argues some Truths are neer the birth, which he would deale withall, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> with the Hebrew Children, indeavouring to stifle them in the birth, many being so astonished and amused, that they sit down with what the most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, fearing all beyond that to be Heresie; we should be equally as free to Truth, as fearefull of Error. To be hide-bound to Truth, is as bad, if not worse, than to be catching of Error. Let every Truth have its full value and place: He that accounts slightly of the least Truth, so farre he accounts little of Christ, and despises
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178839:4"/> Christ: Its the humour of our Politicians to practise onely Popular and State-wayes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, courted by the multitude: as for others, they are indifferent, well if they contain from Persecution. They that goe with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, will sooner take up stones to throw at Truth, than Scriptures, to examine Truth by. The least Truth contains Christ in the bowels of it, and to a godly heart weighs more then the Earth. Every Truth is a beame of God, and when espoused to the Soule by the Spirit of God, it assimulates to God, and sanctifies and becomes the inscription of God drawn out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the soule. Look not what Truth is of most note in the World, but what is owned by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; what agrees not with it, <hi>omnibus numeris,</hi> is false and crooked. The Scripture is Gods Oracle, Truths Chaire of State; there we must consult her, and no where else. And how infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely are we beholden to the mercy and grace of God, that when there is but one onely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rule in all the world, God doth so farre condescend to our weakenesse, as to make it plain and easie in all practicall points. Lets exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all we refuse, and receive, with much selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniall, Prayer, conference, forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178839:4"/> renouncing our own parts and wisedome, depending upon him, who is the Father of light, the Prime and Originall truth. I would not be understood, as Judging any who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minded. I remember the whole streame of the practise of the godly, is generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst: with the greater humility therefore, I desire to declare my differing light, proposing to their examination, and enquirie all that shall be said. Whatsoever our differences be herein, let us still mind the maine, and keep within the Golden Rule; Remembring, that God hath called us unto Peace and Love, not to Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Bitternesse; and let every one be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded in all these things in his owne minde, and so let him walke, (not offending other Brethren in their practize) onely see that he fetch his Light from, and Ground his Practise upon the Word of God, which we must fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low as our Pillar of Fire, and Pillar of Cloud.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
            <p>THe Seventh day, Recorded in the fourth Commandement, hath been generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and reputed <hi>Jewish,</hi> and so buried
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178839:5"/> amongst Ceremoniall Rites. To be ashamed or a scare of Truth, because of Nick-names, and the little repute it hath in the world, argues want of Love unto, or knowledge of Truth. The Scribes and Pharisees call Christ <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> to make people afraid to look at him, or owne him: It matters not by what Names or Titles men call things, but what Name soever God putteth upon any thing, that shall stand good, and every thing shall be called by its right and proper name at the last day. <hi>Truth</hi> is often suspected, because of odde Names put on it by the artifice of Satan, to hinder men from being inamoured with the lovelinesse and beauty of it; and oft Error goes so neatly drest and atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that though it have no naturall beauty of its own, it passes currant with those who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see so clearly into the nature of things. Its a time for us to weigh every thing at the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuary. Theres nothing so down weight, so plain and perspicuous, which the inventions of men cannot finde out many witty and probable objections against. If the seventh day be found to have the double appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and witnesse of the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, its sufficient security for our subjection
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178839:5"/> and obedience. Consider it in its first Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and thats as ancient almost as Man, and more ancient then sinne it selfe; for some hold, That <hi>Adam</hi> fell the first seventh day, on which also Christ was Promised. The first seventh day God himselfe kept, resting from all his work, and delighting himself in looking over all that he had made, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. &amp; 2.2.<note place="margin">Ains<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</note> The Hebrew Root for seven, signifies <hi>fulnesse, perfection:</hi> and the Jews held many Mysteries to be in the number seven: So <hi>John</hi> in his <hi>Apocalypse</hi> useth much that number: As, seven Churches, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Starres, seven Spirits, seven Candlesticks, seven Angels, seven Seales, seven Trumpets: and we no sooner meet with a seventh day, but its blessed; no sooner with a seventh man, <hi>Enoch,</hi> but he is Traslated. The Sabbath was given to <hi>Adam</hi> in his State of Innocency, long before the Institution of the Jewish Church, and so was Moral, given to all Nations, as other Lawes engraven on mans heart by God himselfe; not Cerimoniall onely, as some would have it; it was founded in Paradise it selfe, and so stands exempt from the number of those Figures and Types that were to dye and expire with the Death of Christ; for whatever
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178839:6"/> was simply Jewish and Typicall, then received its desolution from his satisfying Crosse. This seventh was observed by all the holy Patriarkes before the Law: And God himselfe observed it when he rained Manna, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.12. he keeps to his own Institution. When he comes to In act, and make it into a Law, among other Morall and perpetuall Statutes and Ordinances, he praefaceth more especially before it, and puts a solemne Memento upon it, to show how cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious he is, and would have us to be of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day. We should remember how God kept it, how the Saints in Heaven keep their Sabbath, and doe like them in Prayses, Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings, Admiring the Eternall love of Christ, and of God, who both of them Rested from their Work on the seventh day. <hi>Remember to keep holy the seventh day.</hi> A speciall frame of holinesse, should be then upon our Hearts, more then ordinary, which we should labour to keep and weare all the six dayes after. And the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is very positive <hi>for the seventh day,</hi> take away the day, and the Morallity of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand seems to be destroyed. God saith not, Keep holy a seventh day, but <hi>the seventh day;</hi> as if he would have no other day but <hi>that.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:178839:6"/> What is there more Jewish in that, then in the second, fifth, or tenth Commandements. We shall finde it <hi>Isay</hi> 58.13. &amp; 56.1.2.4.6. <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> 20.12.16.21.24. &amp; 22.8.9. placed among those things that are not Legall Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, but of perpetuall universall observance among the Saints and People of God, in all Ages and Places; God intending that this should out-live the lump of Ceremonies. It stands placed in the middle of the Decalogue, as that which hath aspect both wayes; To our duties to Man, and to God, a common tye and ligament between both Tables. God remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to keep day and time with us; and its but just, that we should remember to <hi>keep</hi> his day. Those two Tables were the Writing of the Finger of God himselfe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.18. &amp; 32.15.16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.10. and contained nothing Ceremoniall, but what is Morall and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the Letter of it. First God practises it; and then he Writes it as a Law. And when God comes to make the New Covenant (the Covenant is the same alwayes, onely made in a New manner in Christ the Mediator) he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises to Write his Laws in our Hearts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. even the same that he Writ with his Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178839:7"/> Writing, argues the subjecting of the soul to him, transcribing them upon the soule, and thereby transforming the soule unto the holy nature of the Law. And of this Law, written with the Finger of God in two Tables, speaks Christ, <hi>That not one title of it shall passe away, untill all be fulfilled,</hi> Mat. 5.18. Luke 16.17. Christ fulfilled, but never abolished this Law. The hand-writing of Ordinances that was to be blotted out, and was contrary unto us, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. is not meant of the Morall Law, in its Morall Observation, but of the Ceremoniall Law, or of the Law as a Covenant of Works, that had a curse annexed unto the not doing of it, which no flesh was able to doe and performe, but Christ onely, our surety; his blood hath blotted it out, that we have nothing to doe with it, nor it with us. And in that sence Christ dyed to take away the Law; so as we may say with <hi>Luther, Lex nostra Christus est.</hi> VVe should <hi>know</hi> no Law, no command, but Christ. <hi>Lex Diabolus est in Conscienscia,</hi> where it is praedominant in the Conscience. Its <hi>Agar,</hi> the Bond-woman, which is to be cast out, as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite unto the Promise and Covenant of grace in Christ, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.23.24. Though the Law must
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178839:7"/> not be a Saints Principle, yet it must guide his practise. The Morall Law is called, <hi>The Tables of the Covenant,</hi> Heb. 9.4. which were in the <hi>Arke,</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of Christ. In the <hi>Arke</hi> was the <hi>Mannah, Aarons Rod</hi> that Budded, the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Covenant:</hi> nothing but what is perpetuall was in the <hi>Arke,</hi> those signifying (as some think) the Sacraments, the Ministery, the Moral Law. After our being in Christ, we are more bound to keep the Law, then before: Grace is a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Law, as its a beame of the holy nature of God. The strength of sinne that lay in the Law, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. is taken away by the sight of pardon, and satisfaction through Christ; and so the Law becomes as a dead Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and we dead to it (that hath no more power over us, as to Guilt, or Obedience) when once we are Married to <hi>Christ,</hi> our second Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, by vertue of which Marriage, we bring forth all the fruits of our acceptable Obedience to God; and no other Obedience he owns, but what springs from that match, or union, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.1. <hi>to the</hi> 5. <hi>The Law</hi> then, as to our practise, was alwayes Morall, even in Paradise it selfe; and what was once Morall, cannot be made afterward Typicall. What more Jewishnesse,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178839:8"/> or Typicalnesse, in the fourth Commandement, then in the second, <hi>Thou shalt make thee no Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Image.</hi> The Papists, in oppositions to the Jews, fill all their Churches and Temples with Pictures and Images, falling down before them, and worshipping, as they say, God in them, or by them, to the just scandall of the Jews, and hardening them against the Christian Doctrine. Circumcision was Typicall, signifying <hi>Christ</hi> to come, and to dye, and be cut off in our flesh; and was properly called, <hi>A yoke,</hi> by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles themselves, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. and the Urgers of it charged with subvertion of the <hi>Soules</hi> of the Disciples, <hi>Verse</hi> 24. saying, <hi>They must be Circumcised, and keep the Law, unto whom we gave no such command.</hi> The Law there, is to be understood of the whole Ceremoniall Law, to the keeping whereof, Circumcision bound then, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. But for the Morall Law, <hi>James,</hi> one of the Principall composers of that Letter, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressely charges the observation of it upon all Christians, <hi>James</hi> 1.25. &amp; 2.8.9.10.11. and he calls it, <hi>The Royall Law, The Law of Liberty.</hi> For Obedience and Holinesse is the greatest badge of a Christians Honour and Liberty. None is so free as he that lives most by Rule;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178839:8"/> none so Noble as he that is most subject to the Law of God. But what charge was there ever brought by any Apostle against the Sabbath, for being a <hi>yoke,</hi> which is given to us for a day of spirituall delights, to be spent in holy rest, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, ordinances, and all good works? what more <hi>yoke,</hi> or Jewishnesse in the rest of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, then of the first? If the Day was Typicall, the rest was Typicall also; and both did end in <hi>Christ,</hi> as some say, who was Gods rest, and ours too; and so we should have no day of holy rest. A man may be Jewish in imposing too much upon the bare <hi>Letter,</hi> or out-side of an Ordinance, but cannot be too strict in the spirituall disposition, and bent of his heart in it. Men disclaime the seventh day as Jewish, against which, no Apostle spoke or writ; and yet they will make use of the <hi>Jewish Circumcision</hi> to prove Infant Baptisme by, which no Apostle made use of ever to that purpose, but witnessed against it, as wholly abbrogated, and subverting mens soules. In the Old Testament then, the seventh day stands without contradiction Gods holy and blessed day, sanctified, and set a part for a day of rest and holy meditation, and as a remembrance, earnest, and pledge of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178839:9"/> of <hi>Christ</hi> upon Earth. That time shall be all Sabbath, nothing but Sabbath, Rest, and Triumphing with <hi>Christ.</hi> This Sabbath points at that, and seales to us that great Sabbath of rest, which is yet remaining to the people of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sabbatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Firmum, id est, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batizandum esse populo Dei, <hi>Trem.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. The word is, a <hi>Sabbatisme,</hi> a keeping a Sabbath: The same word is Read be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law, <hi>Exodus</hi> 16. The Sabbatisme, the Sabbath of holinesse; And after the <hi>Law, Exod.</hi> 31.15. The Sabbath, of <hi>Sabbatisme,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse to Jehovah. <hi>Ainsworth.</hi> The Apostle doth not disprove, disanull the seventh day; but by it he proves, That there is a Rest remaining to the Saints, after all the afflictions and persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this World; a peculiar day of Rest, and Sabbath, after their weary six dayes trouble and toyle. The Jewish Doctors say, the World shall continue 6000 years (which shall end with the slaying of the Witnesses, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. &amp; 10.6.7. as <hi>Christ</hi> was Crucified immediately before the Sabbath) so our great Sabbath will be, as some hold, the 7000 yeare of the World, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4. that shall be the time of our refreshment, that shall come from the presence of the <hi>Lord,</hi> (it may be <hi>Christs</hi> personall presence) and a time of restitution of all things spoken of by all the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178839:9"/> holy Prophets, since the World began, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.21. As sure as ever we Celebrated any se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, we shall that, a solemne time of rest and rejoycing with Christ; and before then, the seventh day cannot be dissolved. Not <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> but <hi>Paul,</hi> makes it a <hi>Type,</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of rest in Christ, and with Christ, and so continue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the authority of it, by making it a <hi>Type</hi> of rest yet remaining to the Saints. If the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath signifie a <hi>Sabbatisme</hi> to come, it must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue till it come. If Baptisme signifie the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection</hi> of the Dead, it must continue till that first Resurrection, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 29. If the Lords Supper signifie our sitting and feasting with Christ in his Kingdome, and the great preparation he is making for us against that day, it must also continue till Christ come, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29.30. All Gospel-Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces signifie and seale somewhat <hi>Christ</hi> is yet to doe for us in his own Person, as well as some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what he hath already done in us by his blessed spirit; they are of that authority left us in the last Will and Testament of <hi>Christ,</hi> that nothing can dissolve the practise of them but <hi>Christs</hi> Personall presence, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. and then they shall all be put down. We should be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178839:10"/> continually thinking, and longing after this Kingdome, as <hi>Christ</hi> hath taught us to Pray, <hi>Thy Kingdome come:</hi> the frequent remembrance of it will beget singular frames of patience, and holinesse, in the middest of all our afflictions, troubles, tryals, mockings, oppressions, tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: We ought to think much of this great and last Sabbath, when we shal remember all our sufferings, with Prayses, and have a sufficient amends made us for all our indurings for <hi>Christ;</hi> Every Sabbath should be to us, as if we were already treading upon the borders of this great Sabbath, ready to fit down with <hi>Christ</hi> in his Kingdome, who then will be Sabbath, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, Supper, Word, Temple, Sunne, Moone, all to us, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.22.23. As for the time of the beginning of the Sabbath, Gods time and order is best, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>The Evening and the Morning were the first day,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.32. <hi>From Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Evening you shall rest your Sabbath.</hi> After <hi>Christs</hi> Buriall, the sixth day at Evening <hi>the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath drew on, Luke</hi> 23.53.54. <hi>Sabbatum a Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere Dei veneris incipit, orto syder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quod Lucifer dicitur,</hi> Trem. <hi>in loc.</hi> Some count from Sunne set to Sunne set; others, from Bed-time to Bed-time. Its but equity to give God his full time,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178839:10"/> which way soever we count. As for that which some doe object, That the seventh day cannot be Morall, in regard there are some places in the world where it cannot be observed; as where it is altogther Day or Night for a full halfe yeare together, (neer the North Pole, &amp;c.) it is too frivolous to make an Argument of, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a want of better, where a man is ready to take up any light thing next at hand. Where there are not six days to work in, there cannot be a seventh to rest in. In the most part of the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table world, there is Night and Day, six Dayes, and the seventh. And the right seventh Day, <hi>Rome</hi> her selfe, (who yet calls it <hi>Dies Sabbati,</hi> not <hi>Saturni,</hi> as shee doth the other Week Dayes by Heathenish Names: and shee probably will be found to be the first that substituted the first Day of the Week.) <hi>Rome</hi> received it from the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who still <hi>keep</hi> that Day every where, and when it shall please God to bring them in, they shall bring in with them much light to the Scriptures, to Prophesies, to Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to this point of the Sabbath also.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:178839:11"/>
            <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
            <p>NOw let us come and enqure of the New Testament,<note place="margin">Magnopero eurandum est, ut id te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neamus quod semper, quod ubi{que} quod ab omnibus Prophetis, &amp; Apostolis, ereditum &amp; eraditum hoc vero Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicum est.</note> and consult the <hi>Writings</hi> and practises of the holy Apostles, and of <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe, to whom the Legislative Power of repealing and making Laws and Ordinances for his Church doth onely appertain, by vertue of his Mediatorship. VVhere is the seventh Day abrogated, or repealed? Nay, where is it named, that it is not rather ratified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and set apart to holy rest? And the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath in the New Testament every where, will beare no other signification, then that of the seventh Day, at first Instituted by God, which we cannot, with any warrant, throw in, and bury amongst Antiquated, Dead Jewish Rites, when God himselfe hath so clearly Recorded it. a standing and living command (as we have spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) in the Decalogue, among things of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, necessary, and perpetuall use. And that command (which no other is) is partly affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy;</hi> and partly negative, <hi>In it thou shalt not doe any Worke,</hi> (that is, any Laborious <hi>worke,</hi> Calling
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178839:11"/>
               <hi>worke,</hi> six dayes <hi>worke;</hi> for <hi>workes</hi> of Necessity, and Charity, <hi>it</hi> not onely permits, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands) where that Maxime of Divines hold good, <hi>Negativum Praeceptum ligat semper,</hi> &amp; <hi>ad semper,</hi> &amp; <hi>in negativis major est Emphasis.</hi> And <hi>it</hi> restrains the not doing of any work to that very Day. <hi>In it.</hi> And God sanctified <hi>it;</hi> and hallowed <hi>it;</hi> and blessed <hi>it.</hi> The force of the command runs out upon the Day; and should a man make any other day of Rest, it were his own day, not Gods. Now our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jesus Christ sayes plainly of this Morall Law, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17.18.19.20.21. &amp;c. <hi>That he came not to destroy, but to fulfill the Law.</hi> The Ceremoniall Law he fulfilled and abolished: The Morall Law he fulfilled and established.<note place="margin">Lex cessavit in mysteriis, manet tamen in Praeceptis <hi>Haymo.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Christ</hi> destroyes not the Letter of the Law, but confirmes it: And that he shews, by putting a more spirituall and holy sence upon the Text of the Law, then the Scribes and Pharisees ever did, or could; who onely rested in the bare Letter, or Literall sence of the Law. The Gospel puts a more spirituall Interpretation upon the fourth Commandement, and injoynes a more holy and spirituall kind of Rest, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the strength it gives, and so we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:178839:12"/> are bound both to the letter and spirit of the <hi>Law,</hi> as being under the Covenant of Grace, and made partakers of a Divine Nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. Christ calls himselfe the <hi>Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> that is, the Institutor, the appointer of it, a Lord Instituting, not Changing. He could easily, with a word of his mouth, have abrogated that day, and set up another in its roome, if he had so intended it should be, doubtlesse he would have given it in charge to his Apostles, either the First day of the Week, when he appeared to them, or some time of those forty dayes after his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, when he abode with them, Speaking and Teaching the things of the Kingdom of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3. And after the death of <hi>Christ,</hi> it is said of those holy Women, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.56. <hi>That they Rested the Sabbath Day, according to the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement;</hi> which, one would thinke, the Holy Ghost hath purposely named, to let us know, that his minde is still to keep up the Authority of that Commandement, as being yet in force, and to answer the scruples that any might make thereabouts. And <hi>Luke</hi> 24 1. The first Day of the <hi>Weeke</hi> was their working day, then they brought their <hi>Spices</hi> which they had prepared,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178839:12"/> the day before the Sabbath, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.1. Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der now the Apostles practise, and you will find this Day, in a speciall manner, set a part to Prayer, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.12. and to Preaching the Word, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.4. <hi>Paul</hi> Preached <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>very Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.14.15. <hi>verses:</hi> and the 42.43.44. <hi>verses. Acts</hi> 17.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.21. For the <hi>Jewes</hi> divided their Law into fifty two Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, one of which, and a Lecture out of the Prophes, they Read every Sabbath, so Read the the whole <hi>Law</hi> over in the space of a yeare: Read those Places, besides many more. <hi>Object. They did not allow the Day, onely tooke the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that Day to Preach. Sol.</hi> That had been too grosse temporizing, for the Apostles to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish a Jewish Ceremony, and never to speake against it, or write against it; It were to charge them with unfaithfulnesse. They were plaine enough in the abrogation of Circumcision, the highest piece of Judaisme. <hi>Paul</hi> would have been as bold with Judaizing herein, as he was with <hi>Peter, Galat.</hi> 2.11.12.13.14. Further, Christ himselfe Preached constantly on that Day, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16.17. &amp;c. The day of Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cost af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Christs Resurrection) pouring out of the spirit, converting three thousand, Baptizing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178839:13"/> them, adding them to the Church, was upon the Sabbath day, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1.26.41.46. and this is the first Publique Church-meeting that we Reade of. A Church they were before the death of <hi>Christ. Christ</hi> was the first Officer. The Apostles the first Members. For they were all Baptized, and received all the Lords Supper, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed all Acts of Communion before <hi>Christs</hi> Death. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4. we reade that the Apostles were Assembled together, or Eating together, (that was one speciall act of Communion in those dayes, <hi>Eating together, Acts</hi> 2.46. to which also was commonly annexed Prayer and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation one of another) and <hi>Christ</hi> Personal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them. And it was the last meeting that he had with them, he went to Heaven from that meeting, and it was a Church meeting too, (to shew, that he could finde in his heart to live and dye amongst the Saints; if he would be in any place upon Earth, he would be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them in the Church, as the next best to Heaven; he hath no other Heaven upon Earth) he goes not to Heaven from the Temple (he never owns that, never appears there, after his Resurrection, to shew the Abrogation of all Temple-worship, and service) but from among
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178839:13"/> his Disciples and Saints, met together in acts of holy Communion. Oh what enemies to Christ were those Bishops, Minister, Magistrates, that would rob Christ of his delight in this world, hinder and persecute the meeting of Saints, jeering at their acts of mutuall love and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship. How hath Christ met with them to purpose both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the yokes of such men from off the Saints neckes? Againe, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.13.14. we reade of another Church meeting, after <hi>Christs</hi> Assenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (the day the Holy Ghost hath concealed from us, as he hath done the day of his Birth; which if we had known, we might have done with it, as the Jewes with the Body of <hi>Moses,</hi> had they known where it layd: God never giving any command, in the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, concerning any day but one; and would have us know no other,) after they had seen him taken up in such Glory, (even as he shall also come again, to set up his Kingdom in the World, <hi>verse</hi> 11.) they got together, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued together in Prayer and Supplication, <hi>verse</hi> 13.14. We never reade of any such phrase as this, asscribed to any first day of the Week. And note by the way, that glorious sights of <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:178839:14"/> makes Saints to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntinue in the use of all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; from seeing <hi>Christ</hi> ascend, they come to Prayer; they got not above Ordinances, and so they were taught by <hi>Christ</hi> to doe, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. &amp; 4. and <hi>Paul,</hi> after that Heavenly Vision, and the immediate sight of Jesus Christ, he is found Praying, <hi>Acts</hi> 9 11. the highest sights of <hi>Christ,</hi> ingages Saints most to all duty, Men that are off, or above Ordinances, are not under glorious sights of <hi>Christ.</hi> And we may further note by the way, That in those forty dayes <hi>Christ</hi> was with them, (teaching them the things of the Kingdome of God) he never taught them to observe the first day of the Week, as a holy Sabbath; for if he had, the Apostles in some of their Writings, would have Recorded so speciall a Law of his Kingdome. And also in the same Chapter, we Reade of another <hi>Church-meeting,</hi> in the 15. <hi>verse,</hi> about the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a new Apostle, and that with Prayer also. Of all those severall <hi>Church-meetings,</hi> we doe not Reade any mention made of the day on which they were. But as we were speaking, the day of Pentecost, in the second Chapter, (the first Sabbath we meet with in this book) was the day of the first Publique <hi>Church-meeting,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:178839:14"/> of that first Mother Christian Church, (which continued a pure Virgin 66. yeares, before shee degenerated, and had about 16. Bishops, all Jewes, succeeding one another, <hi>Euseb.</hi>) wherein, the Preaching of the Word, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, were Publiquely Administred, <hi>verse</hi> 41. and that this day of Pentecost was the seventh day, is plain from <hi>Leviticus</hi> 23.15.16. the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath there mentioned is the day of Passeover, (the same day that <hi>Christ</hi> Celebrated the Passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over with his Disciples, <hi>Marke</hi> 14.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.7. instituted the <hi>Supper,</hi> was <hi>betrayed,</hi> which was the fifth day of the Week) a great Feast of the Jewes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.2. Now they were to count from the morrow after that Sabbath or Feast, (that is, from the next day, which was the sixth day of the Week, on which <hi>Christ</hi> suffered fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes they were to account, and the fiftieth day, would fall upon the Sabbath, or seventh day, the morrow after the Sabbath being to be counted the first of the fifty. So they kept the same Pentecost, with the Jews.</p>
            <p>Thus the Apostles practised, and if the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of the seventh day had not continued in force, they would have mentioned the repeale thereof, and layd a prohibition upon the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:178839:15"/> as to the further observation of it. For that notion of Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> seems to be harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous to Truth, That all Laws meerly Jewish, were before <hi>Christs</hi> death <hi>Vivae,</hi> at his death <hi>Mortinae,</hi> after his death <hi>Mortiferae;</hi> than that great Jewish Ordinance of all, Circumcision, was discharged, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.3. <hi>If ye be Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Christ shall profit you nothing. Acts</hi> 15.1.10. those that taught Circumcision, they are taxed by <hi>Peter, Why tempt ye God, to put a yoke upon the necks of the Disciples, which neither we nor our Father were able to beare?</hi> But no such Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, the New Testament puts upon the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, it not being any appurtenance of the <hi>Jewish Church</hi> state onely. What new day of Gods appointment, doth the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hold forth unto us, to be wholly observed as a Sabbath of rest? In this seventh, the Old and New Testament both conspire; <hi>Et quod an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquissimum id verissimum.</hi> Scripture knowes no such distinction, as of a <hi>Jewish</hi> and a <hi>Christian Sabbath;</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> did not observe one day, and the <hi>Christians</hi> another. The <hi>Church</hi> at Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem kept the same <hi>Sabbath</hi> the Jewes did; and if they did keep the first day of the Week a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> then they kept two dayes together, of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178839:15"/> ceasing from their Callings, for many of them being Mechanicks, it is not probable that they did open their shops, and worke of their Trades upon the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> and as little probable, that they did Rest wholly from their Callings the day after the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> we never heare of any difference between the Jewes and the Disciples about that point, (onely about two hundred years after <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euseb.</note> there were a sort of <hi>Hereticks</hi> in <hi>Palaestine,</hi> called <hi>Archontici,</hi> which referred the Creation of all things unto many Powers, they said, the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was the God of the Jewes, and that the Devill was the Son of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi>) if the Apostles dayes had afforded any dispute of that kind, we should have had an account of it, as well as about Circumcisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. which was meerly Jewish. If ever the <hi>Brethren</hi> had scrupled at it, it would have come into debate in that Counsell of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles; had the <hi>Brethren</hi> not observed it, the Jewes would have found fault; for so supers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious were they of that day, that they questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Christ</hi> and the Apostles but for plucking the eares of Corne upon that day, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.1. And S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Luke Acts</hi> 1.12. makes mention of a <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> dayes journey, which was about two short
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178839:16"/> miles, it not being lawfull to travell further on that day, they so observing it, <hi>Ex veterum Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione. Luke</hi> makes use of it to describe the distance of place, but doth not reprehend it as a Jewish error. <hi>Christ, Mat.</hi> 24.20. bids them Pray, <hi>their Flight be not in the Winter, nor on the Sabbath.</hi> The Winter is unfit for flight; the Sabbath was appointed of God for holy rest; those would be agravations of their tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. He doth not tell them of the change of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> after his death, but confirmes it; for <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was not destroyed till about forty yeares after. And the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 14.5.6. discoursing onely of the six dayes, prefers not the first day of the <hi>Weeke</hi> before any other of the fix, being all equall of themselves, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Weeke</hi> day a <hi>working</hi> day; neither doth he there lay down any thing against the rest of the seventh day, which all acknowledged, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred above other dayes, in regard of that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Gods command stampt upon it. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. he dashes out <hi>Jewish Holy dayes, New Moons, Sabbaths,</hi> (Festivall Ceremoniall Sabbaths) which were of Gods appointment also, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for that <hi>Church state;</hi> but he <hi>keeps</hi> off from the least reflection upon the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> as a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178839:16"/> figure, he derogates nothing from it; and if he had received any order therein from the Lord, he would have delivered it to us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3. (for whatsoever <hi>Christ</hi> commanded, the Apostles taught and practised, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.) and in the fourth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rse of that Chapter, he speaks of the very day of <hi>Christs</hi> Resurrection; but doth not in the least, hint any thing to make it a Sabbath, which he might fitly have done here, if it had been the mind of <hi>Christ.</hi> And where be expresly names the seventh day, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.4. (the very last place where the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>venth day is named) he is so farr from detracting fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m its authority, or from declaring it null, and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated, that he names it with its first institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-character, and gives it the same title it had at first, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2. and this in his Epistle to the Hebrews, who were the great observers of that day; which if it had been changed, or its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority worne out of date, he would not have omitted to have instructed them therein. But where is the speciall character of a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that Scripture doth any where set upon the first day of the <hi>Weeke? Christs</hi> Resurrection, his Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, breaking Bread on that first day, will put no such signall <hi>marke</hi> upon it; whereas in all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178839:17"/> the Evangelists, and Acts of the Apostles, you shall no sooner meet with a <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, but ye shall finde <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apostles doing some <hi>worke</hi> sutable to the nature of that day; but never changing it into a <hi>Working</hi> day. Yea, as God in the sixth day finished his <hi>Worke, Gen.</hi> 2.1. and rested the seventh day, and blessed it; so the Lord Jesus in the sixth day (being the day of his suffering) pronounced concerning his <hi>Worke</hi> of Redemption, <hi>John</hi> 19.20. <hi>It is Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</hi> He beheld with infinite contentment, even from his Crosse Dying, all the <hi>Worke</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly done, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly compleated in reference to our salvation (He who was Innocency it selfe, he hung upon the Tree, as the great Malefactor, in our stead, <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> 23.33. but he saw than and there, all fully discharged, and acquitted, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever in Heaven or Earth might accuse or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest us, as God the sixth day looked over all his <hi>Worke</hi> of Creation, and say it was good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. so did <hi>Christ</hi> also his <hi>Worke</hi> of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption;) this was about the beginning of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> the ninth Houre of the Day (the time of Sacrifices, then dyed <hi>Christ</hi> the great Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for our sins, and put an end to all Legall Sacrifices, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10.11.12.13.) the <hi>Sabbath</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:178839:17"/> drawing nigh, <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> 23.54. Thus the seventh day he rested in the Grave, he rested from his suffering, dying Worke, as God did from his Creating Worke. So that if we judge any <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> of rest to be kept, its safest to keep to that which <hi>Christ</hi> and the Apostles did observe; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse we imagine (as some doe, who are not sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the Authority of the first day of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> as being simply of Divine Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that much lyes in the <hi>Churches</hi> Power,<note place="margin">Calvin. Peter Martyr</note> to appoint any day of the <hi>Weeke</hi> for a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and will rather appoint any day, then the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, fearing the Jewishnesse of it. Others say, every day should be a <hi>Sabbath.</hi> True we should carry every day a Heaven, a <hi>Sabbath</hi> about in our hearts. But we must not confound things that God hath made distinct. God hath distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished between the six dayes, and the seventh, as he hath between the Night and Day, for labour and rest, and we must distinguish where God doth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
            <p>LET us consider those Scriptures which beare the principall authority upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:178839:18"/> of the Godly, <hi>viz.</hi> The Resurrection of <hi>Christ</hi> upon the first day of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> his appearing to his Disciples upon that day, <hi>John</hi> 20. breaking Bread upon that day, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Collections upon that day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. and the Lords day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. Let appeale be made to Scripture, the judge of truth, before which, all cases of Conscience must be brought and tried, whether all those places layd together, do carry the force of a command for the solemnizing the first <hi>Weeke</hi> day, or the change of the seventh. God never repealed any act, for any Jewish Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, but if he intends to su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stitute ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the roome of that, he draws up a new one, in as cleare and expresse termes in the Gospel: and its a word of command from God, which makes an Institution; this the first day hath not. God commanded Circumcision, Baptisme, Supper, Preaching, Praying, and so <hi>Sabbath,</hi> with his own mouth, and example; but he is silent, as to any command for the first day, or the change of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> Master <hi>Shepheard</hi> (that pretious Minister of <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thes. Sabbat.</note> and glorious Lampe of the Sanctuary) makes <hi>Christs</hi> Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection the maine Argument of all, for the change of the day: but where doth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:178839:18"/> make it so? Why the Resurrection of <hi>Christ,</hi> more then <hi>Christs</hi> Birth, or his Assention, or his Death, or his lying in the Grave, where he kept the seventh day in the rest of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? <hi>Psal.</hi> 16.9. when also his Soule rested in Paradise, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43. even as <hi>Adam</hi> was the first seventh day (according to the judgement of some) cast out of Paradise; for he was not intended to be the Person that should give us rest, but the second <hi>Adam,</hi> he was to be the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker, to bring us to a better Paradise, a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Sabbatisme,</hi> from which we could not fall, as <hi>Adam</hi> did, and we all in him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. Christ never intended the first day of the <hi>Weeke</hi> should be kept in remembrance of his Resurrection, if he had, he would haue tould us, <hi>John</hi> 14.2. for he tells us all he intended, <hi>John</hi> 15.15. he hath concealed nothing from us, but hath given us command as concerning every thing, <hi>John</hi> 15.14. The <hi>Sabbath</hi> indeed may be a sweet memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of <hi>Christs</hi> rest in the Grave, (thither he carried all the sinnes of Beleevers into those chambers of death, and there shut them up for ever, never to come forth, or rise any more) so also of Gods rest in <hi>Christ,</hi> being well pleased in him, as having finished all his worke, and so
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:178839:19"/> pleased him to the heart, as a compleat, exact performer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. But God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted other speciall Ordinances of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, wherein we celebrate the remembrance of his blessed Death, and Resurrection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.4.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. In Baptisme (not sprinkling) we doe professe and acknowledge,<note place="margin">Non solum propter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missionem peceatorum Baptizamur sed propter Resurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem carnis nostrae, <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Christ</hi> was Dead, Buried, and Raised again from the Dead the third Day, and that we shall rise at the last Day, in the same bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to raign with him. In Baptisme we also pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that we are dead with <hi>Christ,</hi> buried with <hi>Christ,</hi> having all our sins forgiven; quickened with him, risen with him spiritually in our own persons, (as wel as representatively in his Person) and that through the Faith of the operation of God, which Faith is begotten in us by the same operation, power, and omnipotencie of God, that Christs Resurrection was made of, and so no common worke; but even like as Christ was raised up from the dead by the glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we also should walke in newnesse of life: Thats the end of all Baptisme, and so doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect a new creature, one already raised from the dead, and none else. We may demand also by what warrant is <hi>Christs</hi> appearing to his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:178839:19"/>
               <hi>John</hi> 20. made a ground of Institution for the first day. <hi>John</hi> 21.14. its said, <hi>This is now the third time that Jesus shewed himselfe to his Disciples;</hi> and if it were the first day of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> they had not yet learned to keep it for a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> for they were then fishing at the Sea of <hi>Tiberias,</hi> verse 1. he appears to them in their very Calling, shewing, that he blesses, and sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies our lawfull Callings and Labours, and that we should expect the presence of <hi>Christ</hi> in them, and so carry in them, that they may become Ordinances of conversing with Christ; and we are never right in them, but then: he teaches not his Disciples to give over their fishing Trade, but gives them his presence in it. Its the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Christ, to be Diligent, Holy, Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our Calling. We are not to throw away our Callings, as some Monkes, Fryars, and others doe. I remember a Story, I take it is of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Anthony;</hi> he lived an Hermite in a Wood, devoted to Prayer and Meditation; of which being proud, an Angel appeared, bids him to goe to such a Towne, and he should find a Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler a farre more holy man than he. Which he did, came, and found the Cobler hard at his worke, working and speaking sweetly of <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:178839:20"/> working and breathing out Heaven, such a tincture of glory upon his heart, so excellent in Prayer and Conference, that he returned asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of himselfe, and ever after more low in his owne eyes. He exercised more grace at his Awle, than S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Anthony</hi> at his Altar, and shamed his solitary Pride, with his poor honest Trade. Its a Popish Legend, yet may be of great use to us. For that meeting of the Disciples, <hi>John</hi> 20.19. it is not Recorded that it was to sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a <hi>Sabbath;</hi> neither is any mention made of what they were doing, (though its probable they were Eating, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.14. and Praying, and Conferring together; for such good compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny could not be idle) onely it was at Evening, (it may be after their dayes <hi>worke,</hi> for <hi>Mary</hi> brought her prepared Spices that day to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balme the Body of the Lord, and so to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest her love, which was a custome among the Jews, <hi>John</hi> 20.1. <hi>Marke</hi> 16.1. as a <hi>Weeke</hi> day, which she forbare to doe on the <hi>Sabbath, Luke</hi> 23.56.) and the Doores were shut where the Disciples were Assembled, for feare of the Jews (as is wont in times of Persecution) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a <hi>Sabbath</hi> is here expressed; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, the Disciples, were scarce well perswaded of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178839:20"/>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.17. till that <hi>breaking</hi> of Bread, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.29.30.31. and till he shewed them his hands and side, <hi>John</hi> 20.20. and ver. 26. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eight dayes, which would fall upon the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day of the <hi>Weeke.</hi> If the first had been meant, it would have been said, after seven dayes, that first day being not to be included in the number. Doubtlesse he appeared upon other dayes to his Disciples during the forty dayes of his abode upon Earth, and not upon first dayes onely; but that he appeared unto them the same day he arose, and so soon almost as he was out of his Grave; it argues the great love of <hi>Christ.</hi> And by the way, we may take notice, That that is the right way of Reading the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, when we can Spell <hi>Christs</hi> love out of every Syllable of it; otherwise its but carnall reading, though we should see the Person of <hi>Christ</hi> never so glorious, and should not see him as he is cloathed with love, it would but make a carnall sight of him; it shews his great love, that he could not stay long from his Disciples; he knew they would be doubting, and questioning, and unbeleeving, and apt to be troubled, and he did not love to have them in such frames, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siders the weaknesse of their natures, and longs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:178839:21"/> to have them satisfied: Both before, and after his Death, he expressed abundance of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse over them, as poor weaklings, that could not beare much, and therefore he casts now this first day of his Resurrection to meet them three severall times: Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st the Women, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.9. who shewed greatest love and affection to him, both at his Death and Buriall, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.49 55.56. then he meets two of them in another forme, walking into the Countrey upon the same day, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.11. &amp; <hi>Luke</hi> 24.13. And then he appeareth unto the eleven as they sate at meat, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.26. <hi>John</hi> 20.19. so tender was he, that he was troubled, to see a troubled thought in them; and to satisfie them, he would have them to handle him, <hi>verse</hi> 39. and when that would not satisfie, he would eate a piece of a broyled fish, and a hony combe with them, <hi>ver.</hi> 42.43. And he goes yet further, without which, all the rest had been nothing, he opens their understanding also, <hi>verse</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. he never leaves them, till they are fully sati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured. In like manner he deales with all the Saints, in all their do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>btings and questionings; he will have them beleeve, and be satisfied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath done with them; they shall know
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:178839:21"/> him in distinction, from any Spirit or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whatsoever. And when he comes to take his leave of them, <hi>ver.</hi> 50.51. he doth it with the same word that he first pronounced, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.2.3. blessing of them, lifting up his hands and blessing them, and went to Heaven with bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings in his mouth, as if he would assure them, that it should be all his worke in Heaven to blesse them. But if his Resurrection, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, had been grounds of the Institution of a New <hi>Sabbath, Christ</hi> would have been plaine, and open-hearted with us therein, (as his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is to be in all Gospel-Institutions) and not have left it to our Ignorance, and presumption to order. Let us examine that 20 of the <hi>Acts</hi> 7. and we shall finde that neither it will be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull enough to constitute a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> it was onely an ocasionall meeting, <hi>Paul</hi> then being ready for to depart on the morrow. All cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances agree in the proofe of that. The Candles lighted, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. Eating, and then again Speaking untill day-light, and that Eating was about Midnight, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. It must be proved, that the Disciples were together all that day Preaching, Praying, and Sanctifying a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. If <hi>Paul</hi> had Preached that day, its
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178839:22"/> not likely he could have continued all Night Preaching also. And if they had been in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances all day, it is not probable, they could, or would have continued all Night too. So that this place proves rather the contrary. Worthy Master <hi>Perkins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cases of Consci. <hi>cap. 16.</hi>
               </note> useth this as one Argument to prove the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to begin at Morning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s whereas the Jews commonly held the naturall day to be from Sun-set to Sun-set. What Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument as to the day or time of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> can be drawne from this extraordinary Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Night, and Eating than? <hi>Paul</hi> doth not keep this as any part of a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires now at his parting (and words than spoken use to sticke closest) to vent his heart fully to them, he chooseth all the Night to doe it in, to manifest his abundant Love and desire towards them. And that Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, spoken in the seventh and eleventh <hi>verses,</hi> was not Eating the Lords Supper; for in no place this Phrase <hi>Fractio Panis,</hi> breaking Bread, is taken for the Lords Supper. The first place where that Phrase is used, is <hi>Luke</hi> 24.35. and hath relation to <hi>Marke</hi> 16.14. where he Appeared to the eleven as he sate at Meat; the same Phrase is <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. and the 46.47. <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:178839:22"/> they did eate their meat together with single<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of heart, (which shewes the pleasant uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and order among those Primitive Christians, who were as <hi>Zebulon,</hi> keeping ranke, and not of a double heart, of a heart, and a heart; but <hi>d'un caeur entier,</hi> of a Heart all of a piece, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.33.) and gladnesse, praysing God. The dayly and ordinary frames of these first Christians. The like Phrase is <hi>Acts</hi> 27 35. but the Lords Supper is no where recorded, but commonly both Elements are expressed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.21. and 11.23.26.27.28.29. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. and for the most part what signification any Phrase takes upon it where first named, the same it ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Breaking bread, where first named, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies common bread. The first day of the weeke, where first named, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.1.2. <hi>Math.</hi> 28.1. signifies a common week day. The end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> was the beginning of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> or of the six daies wherein they were to labour. The Scripture calls it a <hi>Weeke</hi> day, a <hi>labouring</hi> day, and therefore not a <hi>Sabbath.</hi> The first <hi>Weeke</hi> day, in distinction from the <hi>Sabbath:</hi> So <hi>Baptisme,</hi> where first named, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.6. was administred to such as did repent, and confesse
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:178839:23"/> their sins, and still remains to be the right of no other. The Lords Supper we finde first Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred upon a <hi>Weeke</hi> day at Evening after the Passeover: and so the Apostles and Primitive <hi>Churches,</hi> used it upon any day of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> though its probable, ordinarily upon the first day (after their <hi>Sabbath</hi>) at Evening; and they could bring an Ordinance Spirit, even from their very Trades and Callings to it; which should not hinder us, but fit us for spirituall duties. <hi>Tertullian</hi> saith, <hi>Moris erat convivari,</hi> &amp; <hi>celebrare Coenam Dominicam.</hi> And if they had the Lords Supper, after their love feasts, then they had it dayly, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.1.2. we reade of dayly breaking of Bread, a dayly Ministration, referring perchance to those dayly Eatings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which were usuall when they Assembled together, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4. In the Margine, its <hi>Eating together. Augustine</hi> hath a saying, <hi>Quotidie acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere Coenam Dominicam, nec laudo, nec vitupero.</hi> Ambr. <hi>Per singulos dies offerimus, at una est hostia semel oblata, non multae.</hi> It seems those Primitive Christian, kept those <hi>Agapae</hi> on <hi>Weeke</hi> dayes usually; and in some places, they had the Lords Supper every <hi>Sabbath;</hi> in some places more sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; In some places they celebrated it with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:178839:23"/> the Lords Prayer onely; In other places with one onely Prayer, in forme of a Thanksgiving, or a Hymne. Writers are uncertain. Nothing is certain, but the Scripture; when men have left that, they have been forced to goe to mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Tradition, which whether will it carry us, like an <hi>Ignis fatuus? Harum</hi> &amp; <hi>aliarum ejus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi disciplinarum, si legem expostules Scriptuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, nullam invenies. Traditio tibi praetendetur auctrix, consuetudo confirmatrix,</hi> &amp; <hi>fides observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix,</hi> Tertul. <hi>de Cor. Mil.</hi> &amp; <hi>consuetudo pro lege suscipitur, ubi deficit Lex.</hi> Paul, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>As often as,</hi> &amp;c. (In the Institution, it was Bread broken, not cut at all, they used not severall gestures, but one, sitting all the while, in a Supper posture, and so covered,) its like they had it very often, 20. <hi>ver. When ye come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> he doth not stint or limit them to any time: If he had meant that, he might easily and fitly have put in, <hi>When you come together the First Day of the Weeke.</hi> Onely he saith, <hi>The same Night in which Christ was betrayed;</hi> but no command extant, for binding that Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration to any set day onely; for any day of the <hi>Weeke</hi> there may be Preaching, Praying, and also the use of Baptisme, Supper. So in the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:178839:24"/> Primitive times, Preaching was dayly worke, both in publique and private, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.24. Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion, and Eating together, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46. Dayly searching and examining the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. Dayly di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>puting and reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.17. &amp; 19.9. But that ever the first day of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> was wholly solemnized, and spent in Preaching, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Church-meeting, (as the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was, <hi>Acts</hi> 2 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.44.) we no where finde Registred, the New Testament keeps us onely to a seventh day; and no other day sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord, for a day of rest and cessation from labour. Neither will that place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2. help more to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the first day of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> a holy rest. <hi>Ʋp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the First Day of the Weeke, let every one of you,</hi> &amp;c. it is not said, <hi>Ʋpon every First Day of the Weeke,</hi> neither <hi>upon the First Day of the Weeke when they met together:</hi> Neither <hi>at the Evening of the First Day of the Weeke,</hi> when commonly they met: But, <hi>Ʋpon the First Day of the Weeke.</hi> The Originall is, <hi>In primo Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum.</hi> The same Phrase <hi>Math.</hi> 28.1. there is both <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>First Day,</hi> named. <hi>Gr.</hi> One of the <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> or of the <hi>Weeke. A Sabbatho
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:178839:24"/> tota septimana, ob eximiam dignitatem denominat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r prima Sabbathi. Secunda Sabbathi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jun.</hi> In the <hi>First of the Weeke:</hi> One gives a reason of it thus, <hi>(Quia licitum non erat Judaeis Sabbathis tractare pecunias)</hi> the Jewes would not meddle with money on the Sabbath, and therefore he bids them the first day, &amp;c. It might be in the Morning. The first worke they should doe in the <hi>Weeke,</hi> was a laying by the Lords Penny, as we may call it. They should begin their week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employment, with a dedication of some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of their substance first to God, with an holy offering of what they had to the Lords use. And this is a more Gospel-way for all Church uses, either for maintenance or releife, than that Leviticall, now Papall way of Tythes, the scandall, cloud, and debasement of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery. By this Homage-penny to Heaven, they were to acknowledge, that they held all of <hi>Christ,</hi> and from him expected a blessing upon their labours. As under the Law, the first fruits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d sanctifie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; so this, an earnest-pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that all their <hi>Weekes</hi> gettings should be at his service. That they were not to labour so much for their own, as <hi>Christs</hi> use. A sweet les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for Christians. <hi>Sabbath-dayes</hi> refreshments
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:178839:25"/> should leave behind them generous frames of spirit in us, towards our afflicted Brethren, or others. The duties of the first Table, should prepare us for those of the second. When God hath been bountifull to us, we will be bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his, and will expresse it. The first day of the Week, &amp;c. let every one of you lay by him in store, <hi>Apud se seponat, recondens ut thesaurum,</hi> saith <hi>Beza. Domi suae seponat,</hi> &amp; <hi>servet quod venit in manu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>French Translation</hi> Chacun de vous mette à part pur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers soy.</note> saith <hi>Tremelius.</hi> By him in store: Every one should lay by at his house in store, according to his ability, (somewhat for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife of other Churches, to be ready against <hi>Paul</hi> came, to be given to him, or others, whom they would appoint) or the value of his estate, not of his Incomes that Week. For its possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble some Weeks might make one a great loser, and then he should lay by nothing, who yet may have a standing Estate. He doth not bid them to bring it, and cast it down at the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church-meeting; what Scripture for that practise? It seems to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not so sutable to the Gospel, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.1.2.3.4. <hi>Christ</hi> would have all wayes avoyded, by which vain-glory, hypocrisie might creep in. Religion acts best in secret, when onely under the Eye
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:178839:25"/> of God Reduce Church-collection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to their first Institution, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32.34.35.36.37. <hi>ver.</hi> and 6.2.3. we shall finde the money brought and layd at the Apostles Feet, and Deacons were chosen for the receiving and distribution of it, men qualified with gifts and graces of love and edification, (as the meanest Church-Officer must be) who had the world under their Feet, free from all blemish, suspition of covetousnesse. Laying it at the Apostles Feet implies a more secret and private way of gift. So here, <hi>Lay by him in store,</hi> &amp;c. It seems not probable that they did use so publiquely to make their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, being that some Heathen Persecutor might come in and observe them, and by their freenesse and bounty, have taken an Estimate of their Estates, and brought danger and incoveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon them. For many Christians were convicted for their very Estates. And its likely this was to be a large and free Contribution, which was to supply such a necessity. Therefore he bids them <hi>lay by,</hi> that they might have it in readinesse. But why the first day of the <hi>Weeke?</hi> The holy Ghost speaks not a word in vain, every word hath speciall reason and weight. <hi>The First day,</hi> because following the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> &amp; so more fit
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:178839:26"/> for acts of charity &amp; benevolence than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny other day, they being newly come out of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and having yet the sence of their sweet Communions the day before fresh upon them, and not yet so taken up with their imployments in the world, wherein men are apt to lose the sence of others afflictions. But that this first day here implies a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and Collections to be made than and there in the <hi>Church,</hi> at the Supper, (this being onely an occasionall Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, not constant) I see not. <hi>Paul</hi> telling us how <hi>Christ</hi> Institutes the Supper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.24.25.26. prescribes nothing as to any Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, either at, or after the Supper. I should desire as much a conviction of the least Truth, as of the least sinne. In this matter I would not much contend, knowing much may be said to prove, that matters of order and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie lie in the <hi>Churches</hi> Power: But its safest in every punctilio, to keep strictly to the cleare Rules of Scripture. For Antichrist at first invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly stole in, in very little and triviall things, which seemed indifferent, and to lie in the <hi>Churches</hi> Power. Neither will that <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.10. prove what they intend by it; that Phrase is but this once named in all the New Testament.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:178839:26"/> Could any prove this was the first day, yet it is not <hi>Christs</hi> manner to commend to us a practise of so great importance, as a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> by one sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle witnes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. but how proved that it was the first day of the Week? The <hi>Sabbath</hi> may be called the Lords Day, or Gods Day, <hi>Marke</hi> 2.28. he is called, <hi>Lord of the Sabbath;</hi> he appointed it, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served it in his rest, both at his worke of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Redemption: And if History may be given credit to, <hi>John</hi> at <hi>Ephesus</hi> kept his Easter on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day. But rather, <hi>the Lords day,</hi> from the Lords speciall act of revealing high and hidden things on that day; so great things in the Scripture usually are denominated, <hi>Isay</hi> 2.3. The mountain of the Lord, <hi>Isay</hi> 51.3. The garden of the Lord, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.1. The Arme of the Lord, <hi>Isay</hi> 61.2. The acceptable yeare of the Lord: So the Table of the Lord, the Cup of the Lord, &amp;c. So we call that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Praying, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.9. the Lords Prayer, for the excellencie of the matter and method. Its called <hi>the day of the Lord,</hi> from some speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all discovery of Gods power, greatnesse, love, and mercy towards the creature, <hi>Isay</hi> 2.12. <hi>Joel</hi> 1.15. <hi>Zechar.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Zechar.</hi> 14.1. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:178839:27"/> 5.2. This was that last Revelation, and we are to expect no more Revelations now, having the Scriptures: he saith, <hi>He was in the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. he saw, as it were the day of the Lord, the new Heaven, and new Earth, the Heavenly Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>chap.</hi> 21. &amp; 22. He was so transported in his Spirit, in such a Heavenly trance, as if he had been on the Lords day, (which shall be that great and last day of the World, and the most glorious that ever was) as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was, in the Vision of God, in the Land of Israel, and saw the frame of that City, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 40.2. Every day should be to us, as if we were on the Lords day, beholding <hi>Christ,</hi> and raigning and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing with him in his Kingdome: especially such frames become <hi>Sabbath dayes.</hi> Lay the weight of all those reasons together, in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuary, and try if they will all make up the force of an Institution of the first day of the <hi>Weeke,</hi> or amount to the abrogation of the seventh: What ever we at this day doe ground our practise upon, we may according to Scripture say, <hi>Ab initio non fuit ita.</hi> Truth how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may weare sackcloath for a while over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred with the Majority of Voyces, yet it shall recover strength, and be cloathed with its
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:178839:27"/> Primitive luster and glory, in the Consciences of Saints, notwithstanding all the subtle waies and arts, which Antichrist hath used, to deprave and disfigure Truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
            <p>FOr he hath used, for these many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to force and obtrude upon the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men, his dictates, as infallible Rules, Oracles inspired from Heaven, and so having blinded the world, hath set up himselfe in the Throne of God, and in the Consciences of men, and exalted himselfe above all that is called God; and hath taken upon him to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute and appoint Holy-dayes, Festivall dayes in the <hi>Church,</hi> to be equally observed as Gods Holy day. Nay, the erronious Consciences of men, are made apt to beleeve, through very long custome, That more observance is due to them, than to Gods day, who hath taken to himselfe but one out of seven, and commanded us to labour the other six. This is that little Horne who hath destroyed the fourth Commandment, (for the Romish Church have adulterated the very Letter of the second and fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:178839:28"/> most wickedly. They reade it, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to sanctifie the holy dayes;</hi> meaning their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dayes) both in the negative and affirmative part of it, and so hath undertaken to change times, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. And we shall finde his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger first in the change; for as all the Vessels of the Sanctuary, were carried into <hi>Babylon;</hi> so have all the Ordinances of <hi>Christ</hi> been more or lesse adulterated, corrupted under <hi>Antichrists</hi> raigne; and this of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> among the rest hath suffered. It was a very Ancient, and almost one of the first Controversies that we reade of in History. <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Monuments, <hi>fol.</hi> 48. tells us, how <hi>Easter Day,</hi> was anciently kept upon the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or seventh Day. But one <hi>Hermes,</hi> reputed to be <hi>Pauls</hi> Disciple, having had a revelation, That it was to be kept on the <hi>Sunday;</hi> (so the Heathens called it, <hi>Dies Solis. Rome</hi> first the <hi>Dominica.) Pius,</hi> then Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> Decreed, That it should be accordingly observed in all Churches under his Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And <hi>fol.</hi> 111. he relates a very hot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, that was between one <hi>Wilfride</hi> a Bishop, and one <hi>Coleman</hi> Arch-Bishop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> before <hi>Oswie</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> then present at that dispute, which was about the observation
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:178839:28"/> of <hi>Easter Day. Wilfride</hi> alledged, that S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> kept <hi>Easter Day</hi> the Day after the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath: Coleman</hi> on the contrary, he answereth, That S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>John</hi> kept <hi>Easter</hi> at <hi>Ephesus</hi> the 14. day of the first Moneth, which was the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> both were exceeding hot and stiffe in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. At length the King concluded with <hi>Wilfride,</hi> saying, you both agree on this, That <hi>Peter</hi> had the Keyes left him, and I will not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please <hi>Peter,</hi> the Doore-keeper of Heaven, lest he shut me out when I come to Heaven Gates; and with this simple Argument, satisfied his Conscience; and <hi>Colemen</hi> being discontented, left this Kingdome, and went into <hi>Scotland. Socrates, Schol. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. plainly affirmes, That all the ancient Christians kept their <hi>Easter Die Sabbathi;</hi> and that all the People through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world, doe receive the holy Mysteries every <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> except the People of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> they on the <hi>Sunday.</hi> The <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> (it seems) was generally observed by the <hi>Greeke Churches; Sunday</hi> by the <hi>Latine. Fox</hi> Acts and Monuments, <hi>fol.</hi> 47. reckons its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent chiefly from <hi>Rome,</hi> though to this day, <hi>Rome</hi> keeps the name of the day, and calls <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday,</hi> not <hi>Dies Saturni,</hi> after the Heathen, but
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:178839:29"/>
               <hi>Dies Sabbathi,</hi> after the Christians: The same likewise doth our Parliament records. <hi>Socrates</hi> saith, that some observed both dayes. And <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine in Psal.</hi> 33. <hi>in titulum,</hi> hath a passage, that implyes some such custome among the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, <hi>Titulum Psalmi hujus exposuimus in nomine Domini nostri. Quoniam crastinus dies Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus est,</hi> &amp; <hi>debemus vobis sermonem, differamus in crastinum, ut Psalmi textum libenter audiatis,</hi> To day, saith he, we have expounded the title of the Psalme, because to morrow is the Lords day, we will let alone speaking of the Text till then. Some affirme, that the Heathen by the light of nature, observed the seventh day, which was their <hi>Dies Saturni.</hi> So <hi>Purchas Pil. fol.</hi> 17. <hi>Aretius</hi> saith, <hi>Saturnes day</hi> was sequestred from Martiall and Civill affaires, and esteemed a day most fit for Contemplation and Devotion. And <hi>Fox fol.</hi> 48. B. 30. saith, that <hi>Dionisius</hi> a suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Author, is the first that mentions the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sunday</hi> Holy; whereof we finde no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ancient Authors before his time, except in <hi>Justinus Martyr,</hi> who saith, That the Christians had two times of solemne meeting, which was either to Baptize a new Convert, <hi>(not sprinkle an Infant)</hi> or to keep the Sunday; which was
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:178839:29"/> hallowed by Christian men for two reasons; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause upon that day God made the World; and upon that day, <hi>Christ</hi> shewed himselfe after his Resurrection. When men leave the <hi>Viam lacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> of the Scriptures, no wonder if they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up and downe in uncertainties. Pretious Master <hi>Shepheard, Thes. Sabbat. part</hi> 2. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, that of all practicall Points, he found this most full of knots and difficulties. <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> and the <hi>Rhemists,</hi> ascribe it most to Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they faigne Apostolicall, on which they father all their forgeries. Holy <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> gives much power to the <hi>Church</hi> in constituting one day in seven, as not being tyed to observe one onely, as any one in seven. Others there are, that give it full Apostolicall Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not seeing so clearely into custome, (bred up, and nourished in their Consciences, an infirmitie incident to all of us, as is too evident in some Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> whom yet we dare not but account highly of in the Lord) not so considerately, and impartially examining the Scriptures, to which their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments should bow, which they have with too much facility prostrated to Schoolemen and later Writers. For what Apostle, or Evangelist
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:178839:30"/> ever made the fourth Commandement, or the seventh day, which was before the Law, to be partly Morall, partly Ceremoniall; or can any such distinction, or any thing that beares any tendency to make it Ceremoniall, be found in all their Writings? Or where was the <hi>Dominica</hi> once mentioned in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apostles, or Records of Writers most ancient? unlesse those who are suspected justly, and into which many things have been foisted by the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, who have so bemudded the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of purer Antiquity, that little cleare, or sincere, doth runne downe unto us; onely the holy Scriptures, Gods own Records (of Love and Mercy in the Covenant of Grace made with <hi>Christ</hi> for us) he hath taken care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve undefloured, untouched from the violation of men. These onely we must sticke and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to, therein God hath sufficiently instructed us what will please him in his own Worship, without being beholden to mans invention to modell new things, or raking in the puddle of humane Writers; and in all points of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence whatsoever, we must keep men punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the Scriptures, and question what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they can shew us from thence. If he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:178839:30"/> a day of Rest, its presumption in the best of men to make holy another, (as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant seventh day; but dayes of publique Thanksgivings, Humiliations, should be kept as <hi>Sabbaths</hi> to the Lord) unlesse Apostles had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it from <hi>Christ</hi> to deliver to us. It were to be wished that the names of <hi>Baalim, Hosea</hi> 2.17. were taken out of the mouth of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be remembred no more, and we and our children, taught a purer language. We may stand upon the least punctilio in Religion, so the maine (tendernesse and Love to Saints) be respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The language of <hi>Babylon</hi> doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the children of <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> Its unquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably best, to name dayes as God doth; the first day, the second day, the third day, the fift day, the seventh day. And so first Moneth, fourth Moneth, seventh Moneth, eleventh Moneth, twelfth Moneth; and not after the manner of the Heathen, (they Worshipped the Planets as Gods, and honoured them with the naming their dayes by them, and doing speciall worship to them upon those dayes, imagining each of them to play the god his day about) <hi>Dies Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, Dies Luna, Dies Jovis, Dies Veneris.</hi> Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, Sunday, Thursday, Saterday, &amp;c. January,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:178839:31"/> February, June, July, August, &amp;c.) or of the superstitious Papists, <hi>Christmasse, Candlemasse, Martinmasse, Alhallowmasse, Lent, Pace,</hi> and I know not what other fopperies, the prophane observation whereof, is happily taken away by this Parliament. Other Ordinances there are, wholly almost lost, or much defaced by the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valencie of Antichrist, (and as he more fully shall be discovered, so they shall come neerer to the lustre of their first Institutions.) as <hi>the holy Kisse,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. which was used by the ancient Christians, either when they met one another, to manifest to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then (enemies of the Christian name) the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular love they bore to their fellow Christians, and that they durst own them in the face of enemies; or it may be in publique, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after Prayer, Love Feasts, Lords Supper, as a token of perfect unity, love, conjugall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and singlenesse of heart, free from all prejudice,<note place="margin">De Orat.</note> jealousie and malice. In <hi>Tertullians</hi> time it was used among Christians, he calls it, <hi>Vinculum pacis, signaculum orationis,</hi> &amp; <hi>quae ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio vel communio cum divortio sancti Osculi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegra.</hi> So anointing the sicke with holy Oyle, hath a plaine Institution, <hi>James</hi> 5.14. which
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:178839:31"/> the Pope, Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Ape, hath turned into extreme Unction, and a Sacrament. I have heard of some godly, who have known it pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised upon some sicke with a blessing, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the party. <hi>Trapp. Com. Rom.</hi> 16.16. quotes Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> saying, the Independents at <hi>Arnhein</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> propounded this Kisse of Love to be practised among them, and annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Oyle, and singing Hymnes by one; blaming the holy endeavours of those Saints, to revive those Ordinances in their practise. So Psalmes, Hymnes, spirituall Songs, they were in the Primitive <hi>Churches, Gifts</hi> of the Spirit; as Prayer and Interpretation were, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. a Psalme is mentioned, as performed onely by one, as Doctrine, Revelation, Interpretation was, there must be edification in it, and so it must be a gift. That they had Translated Psalmes, and one Reading, and than all the rest of the <hi>Church</hi> to sing, will be somewhat diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to prove; and that they ought to prove, who would impose any set forme of Psalmes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others, as an Ordinance of <hi>J. C. Colos.</hi> 3.16. they should be so richly fraught with the Word of God, it should inhabite in them in such va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Wisedome, that they should be able to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:178839:32"/> teach and admonish one another every way; yea, so as to be able to translate any word of God into an Hymne, a Psalme, or Spirituall Song, in their hearts first, and than pronounce it, from the power of that inditement. Gifts I say, they were either publiquely exercised, as in that place; or in a more private way of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.19. (they should be so filled with the Spirit, as to speake all in Psalmes, and Hymnes, and Spirituall Songs, (praising straines) not Songs in verse, but such as are the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate inditeting of the Spirit in the Soule, tuned by <hi>Christ.</hi> And that way of singing Psalmes in the heart, every Saint in some measure hath the skill of,) <hi>James</hi> 5.13. (as affliction is to ease it selfe by Prayer, so those holy ebullitions of Heavenly spirituall mirth, are to burst out into Psalmes. Psalmes imply an inward frame of prayses in the heart, and a sutable expression in words by way of a gift, to beget the same praysing frames in the hearts of others. Hearts of Saints are quires of prayses; full of bublings up, and enditings of Heavenly Modulations, <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.1. which makes them like little Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens) but which way soever used, whether in the Church, or alone; spirituall Gifts they were,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:178839:32"/> not read Psalmes, musically sung, as in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Church,</hi> or Poetically Translated into Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as among us Protestants, invented to supply the defect of that gift of spirituall Songs, as formerly the Liturgie, or Book of Common Prayer was brought in, to supply the defect of a gift of Prayer. Psalmes are spirituall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly rejoycings, conceived in the soule by the holy Ghost, and exspressed by speaking, as <hi>Luke</hi> 1.42.46.47. &amp; <hi>cap.</hi> 2.13.14. they did not sing in any Poeticall way. Those ancient Psalmes and Hymnes of the O. &amp; N. Testament, were the immediate breathings of raised inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Soules, filled and transported with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirings of <hi>Christ,</hi> and rejoycings in him; as of holy <hi>Mary, Elizabeth, Zacharias, Simeon:</hi> so <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> being merry, and rejoycing in the Lord with chaines on their heeles, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. they <hi>prayed,</hi> and sung; as they <hi>prayed,</hi> so they sung, (by a gift of the Spirit) not set Formes, not Reading, either of the <hi>Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> or <hi>Davids Psalmes,</hi> that was too much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the gift of the Apostolicall times. Some were wont formerly to say, <hi>Is not the Lords Prayer better then any of our own making; can any Prayer goe beyond that?</hi> We never Reade that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:178839:33"/> ever <hi>Christ</hi> or the Apostles used it; onely he shewes the manner of Prayer, much heart, few words. Long Prayers have, for the most part, great hypocrisie, especially before others, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse the soule be under some strong gales of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall assistance, as oft a Saint will finde he cannot give over, he cannot get away from <hi>Christ,</hi> he is so well heard; and when he is gone, he longs to be at it again. <hi>Christ</hi> puts words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our mouthes, to shew, he loves Prayer, and will as certainly grant it, as he hath bid us Pray; but bids us not to Pray the very Words. I doe not beleeve that ever the holy Ghost did Pen the Book of <hi>Psalmes,</hi> or <hi>Solomons Song</hi> of <hi>Songs,</hi> or <hi>Christs Prayer,</hi> Mat. 6. besides many other <hi>Songs</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> to be set Formes, for than we should never use any other <hi>Prayer,</hi> or <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> they being absolutely the best, better than any man breathing can make; they are not set us as formes, but as Rules, and Coppies for all our holy breathings. What edification, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, doth such singing afford, which the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Text in Scripture (which is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Ordinance of God) doth not afford better and richer. <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> edified one another <hi>by</hi> their songs, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. <hi>they</hi> did not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:178839:33"/> sing the same song, neither did <hi>they</hi> sing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; they were Songs indited in the Heart, from the present sence of mercy. We may make Ordinances to our selves, (as oft we doe spirituall injoyments, forme glorious Images, and Idaeaes of things in our fancies, and set up apprehensions of <hi>Christ</hi> in our own hearts) and thinke them to be reall. No warrant will be found in the Gospel, for set composed Psalmes, more then for set composed Prayer; for singing in Meeter, more then for Musicke, which was used in the Temple, and under the Law. The first Song we Reade of, was <hi>Moses, Exod.</hi> 15. and that was with Musicke, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. In the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there were singers on purpose imployed Night and day, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.53, &amp; 15.16. they had their Instruments also appointed, <hi>ver.</hi> 19.20.21. and Robes of fine Linnen, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5.12.13. Many of these Titles of Psalmes are directed to Masters of Musicke: some Psalmes are Prayers, so <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.19. That singing was peculiar to the Levites, the very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments they played upon, appointed of God. There was a cleare Institution, both for the one and the other, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25. and those singers had civill priviledges, as the Levites had,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:178839:34"/>
               <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.70. &amp; 7.24. Now grant we did come neerer to the first Institution of singing (though they sang the Text it selfe, we the Poeticall sence, which is not to be judged equall with the Text; so that neither did they sing as we doe, nor we sing as they did) yet unlesse such Musicall and Poeticall singing were confirmed in the New Testament, by praecept or practise, it could not hould. For what was practised in the Old Testament, not confirmed in the New, (as the <hi>Sabbath</hi> is) is to be accompted Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. Shew any such Musicall singing, either in the <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> or any <hi>Church</hi> Planted by the Apostles, in their dayes, wherein no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was practized, but what was the exercise of a spirituall gift: If there was Reading, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding did follow, (as in <hi>Christs</hi> example, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.17. to the 23. and in <hi>Pauls, Acts</hi> 13.15.16.) if a Psalme, it was performed by one, as an admonishing gift, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. True! Musicall singing is very ancient, though in Ryme not so, (as the Latine Meeter in the Masse-booke shewes.) In imitation of that Temple-singing, both <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> used Musicke in their Churches; and it hath cost the pens of Learned men some sweat,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:178839:34"/> to defend the use of Organs, now exploded. <hi>Augustine</hi> in his Confession, complaines, That when his heart was not so holily Tuned, yet his affections were tickled and moved, <hi>Flebam uber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimè in Hymnis</hi> &amp; <hi>Canticis suavè sonantis Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae vocibus vehementer affectus,</hi> the loudnesse of Voyces, varietie of Notes, takes mens af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. The ancient Christians had their <hi>Hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos Antelucanos.</hi> Antichrist got in very early into the Church with his Liturgie; and they talke of Saint <hi>James</hi> his Liturgie. <hi>Eusebius</hi> speaks of the ancient forme of singing: And <hi>Ignatius</hi> a Disciple of the Apostles, as they tell us, heard Angels singing Hynes to the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which he brought in to the Church at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch;</hi> corrupt customes are soon introduced, and hold long. The Papists alledge for their practise of Singing and Musicke, the singing of Angels and Saints in Heaven, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.2. those blessed Spirits that live in the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of God, need no Voyces, they sing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sound of words, they are, as we may say, all Tongue, all Sight, all Eares, &amp;c. they have no sences, but what are swallowed up in Glory; they see all in God, and nothing but God; and God is all to them. When <hi>Paul</hi> was a while in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:178839:35"/>
               <hi>Paradise,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. he heard works unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; he calls them words, because we know things onely by words; they in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>words,</hi> but <hi>unspeakeable,</hi> he could not repeat them, they were too big for his expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he lost his tongue, when he did but thinke of them: Scripture uses to ascribe Words, Trumpets, Harps, to the blessed Spirits, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to signifie their glorious praysing, tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing state, in which they are in Heaven, or in <hi>Paradise;</hi> and those praising frames that the Saints carry in their bosomes, in the cleare sights and assured hopes of glory, hould the neerest Analogie with the Hymnes of <hi>Paradise.</hi> It is not the singing, but the matter and heart, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely mixt together, that makes a Hymne. I know not what Hymnes are, if those be not, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.1.5.6. which compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. will evince that singing and saying, comes all to one thing. But that there is Song or Musicke in Heaven, we have no warrant to thinke, if one of these Hymnes were but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by those blessed Spirits, (all turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to praises, and full of all varietie of them) it would incomparably exceed all Song and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke whatsoever. In the Kingdome of <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:178839:35"/> the Saints shall utter praises, that would drown all Musicall Notes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.10.11.12. What way of singing soever we maintain, whether the old Cathedrall way, or the late <hi>Geneva</hi> way, (for Psalmes was first Translated into Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by learned godly <hi>Beza,</hi> and others; the like by other Protestant Churches; and by us in <hi>England,</hi> and so joyned to the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Prayer,</hi> and are still practised very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly among some before their Battells, and otherwise ordinarily) it must be proved that that very way of singing, <hi>Modo</hi> &amp; <hi>Forma, (Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids Psalmes,</hi> or <hi>Solomons Song,</hi> and those Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into Meeter, and first Read, and then Sung in Musicall Tunes, and then all singing together) is an Ordinance of the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, commanded and practised by Christ and the Apostles, or it will fall into the number of humane Inventions. As for that Hymne after the Passeover and Supper, <hi>Math.</hi> 26.30. I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it to be a Thanksgiving, composed and pronounced by Christ; now rejoycing in Spirit, praising the Father, being gladded in his heart for the blessed Institution of his Supper, (the remembrance of his love to us) and now having in his soule, the sence of all
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:178839:36"/> those blessed comforts that all the Saints should enjoy in that Ordinance afterwards; rejoycing also, that the time of his Death drew neere, when he was to manifest the highest testimony of his love to us in his blood and passion; in which Cup also, he had the sence of al the sorrows and bitternesses that ever any Saint was to tast of, and sweetned them. If it were a Psalme of <hi>Davids</hi> (as some conjecture that it was, the 105 Psalme, which the <hi>Jewes</hi> call the <hi>Great Hymne,</hi> and was wont to be sung by them at the Passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over) than it was onely an Appendix of the <hi>Jewish Passeover;</hi> for <hi>Paul</hi> delivering the whole intire Institution of the Supper, in as ample manner as he received it of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 23. he doth not so much as mention the <hi>Hymne,</hi> but leaves it quite out. I mightily transgresse my intended brevtiy. This I freely professe, I am not scandalized at those that see this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of singing, an Ordinance of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, though I cannot; neither ought it to make the least breach in Love or Communion. There is a time comming of the powring out of the Spirit in way of eminency upon all Flesh, both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, Acts</hi> 2.16. which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough it was in part fulfilled in the day of <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacost,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:178839:36"/> yet much remains to be made good to us in the latter times; and we may pleade it as <hi>Christs</hi> promise; all Ordinances and Gifts will be restored neerer the first Apostolicall times, before the end of the slaying of the Witnesses, and before the comming of <hi>Christ,</hi> when Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances shall cease; untill than, we are in all things to give heed unto the blessed Scriptures of the Old and New Testament, as a sure word of Prophesie, 2 <hi>Pet,</hi> 1.19. which contains the whole minde of <hi>Christ,</hi> and are left as his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Legacy in common to all the Saints, in which they have equall right and tnterest, which they are to reade, search, study, and apply, to their own and others comfort, instruction, and edification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26.31.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
            <p>TO Gods holy Institution, the <hi>Jewes</hi> added many superstitions, and irregular observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their own, which God never injoyned, and to which <hi>Christ</hi> opposes that in <hi>Marke</hi> 2.27. <hi>The Sabbath was made for Man,</hi> for Mans good, and his holy refreshment and reposall, <hi>not Man for the Sabbath;</hi> to observe it in such a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:178839:37"/> and ridged way as you doe. Their <hi>Jewis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Doctors say, That danger of life, and works of necessity, did discharge the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> but they were so severe in the point of their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that they tax Christ as not being from God, because he kept not the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> they are scandalized at his most innocent and holy actions; they prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr their <hi>Sabbath</hi> before Christ. So dangerous is it to set up any Ordinance higher than we should, raising it above its due place, <hi>John</hi> 9.16. They censure Christ, the Lord of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and his Disciples, for but <hi>plucking</hi> the eares of Corne on the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> when they were hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, <hi>Math.</hi> 12.1. which Christ maintaines by <hi>Davids</hi> example, was lawfull, as a worke of necessity to be done, and taxes their great ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in such rash consuring, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>If,</hi> saith he, <hi>you had known what this meaneth, I will have mercy and not sacrifice, you would not have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the guiltlesse.</hi> In cases of necessity, God doth dispence with his own Ordinances. With the same ignorance and malice, they labour to accuse him, in the 10. <hi>verse, for healing on the Sabbath day,</hi> which was a worke of Charity, and so necessary to be done; and proves it from their ordinary practise, <hi>That in case a Sheep fall into a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:178839:37"/> pit on the Sabbath day, they will lift it out,</hi> though some later Jews, have more abounded in super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition, even to selfe-destruction. <hi>Purchas Pilg. fol.</hi> 104. tells of a <hi>Jew,</hi> that at <hi>Tewkesbury Anno</hi> 1220. fell into a privie on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> from whence his superstition would not let him be taken out that day; and the Christians cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, constrained him to bide in the next day, their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> where he miserably perished. We reade of one Citie of theirs, 1 <hi>Maccab.</hi> 37.38.39.40.41. against which the enemy came, and they would not so much as resist, or make any lawfull defence on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day; so it was taken, and many hundreds put to the Sword. And <hi>Purchas Pilg. fol.</hi> 447. relates a strange story of this credulous and superstitious people, That upon the report of one <hi>Jew,</hi> that said he had seen the Sabbaticall River; thousands of them, (very rich and wealthy men) left their dwellings, and journied thither, thinking their Messias would appeare to them there; but in the way, they were all miserably wasted, pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and consumed by the <hi>Turke,</hi> and other <hi>Bashaws,</hi> and never came to that River: which is a meer Poëticall Fiction, as the Frence Poët describes it,
<q>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:178839:38"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Du Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, <hi>trois jeur.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>He! pourroy je' oublier q'un Palestrin Ruisseau</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tarit, Religieux, chaque Sabbat fon eau,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Religious River, that the <hi>Sabbath</hi> keeps,</l>
                     <l>Her six dayes streams, than rest from th'Ocaean deeps.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> Yet one is bold to alledge the ceasing of the Sabbaticall streame, as an Argument for the abrogation of the <hi>Jewish Sabbath.</hi> Much given to praejudice, Idolatry, persecution, (which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly goe together) were this people of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> seldome God had them long in any good moode, but they were apt ever and anon, to be making Golden Calves, running into worships of their own making, and mixing tradition of Elders, with Gods commands, not being satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Gods holy and blessed prescriptions, wherein they ought to have rested. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.15.16. describes them fully; <hi>They killed the Lord Jesus, and their own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, have persecuted us, please not God, and are contrary to all men, and wrath is come upon them to the uttermost. Augustine</hi> in his time, blames them much for their idle superstitious way in keeping their <hi>Sabbath. In titulum</hi> Psal. 91. <hi>Ecce,</hi> saith he, &amp; <hi>hodiernus dies Sabbathi est, hunc in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:178839:38"/> praesenti tempore otio quodam corporaliter lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quido,</hi> &amp; <hi>fluxo,</hi> &amp; <hi>luxurioso celebrant</hi> Judaei, <hi>vacant enim ad nugas,</hi> &amp; <hi>cùm Deus praeceperet observari Sabbatum, illi in his quae Deus prohibet excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Sabbathum. Vacatio nostra à malis operibus, vacatio illorum à bonis. Nobis Sabbatum indicit Deus.</hi> Quare? <hi>Primò ubi sit videte, intus est in Corde nostrum Sabbatum. Multi vacant membris,</hi> &amp; <hi>tumultuantur conscientiâ:</hi> a good saying of that worthy Father; This day, saith he, is the <hi>Sabbath day;</hi> and this day the <hi>Jewes</hi> also cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate at this present, but in an idle, luxurious kind of rest; they keep their <hi>Sabbath</hi> onely in trifling away their time; spend it in things which God forbids, and rest from good workes, which God commands: Our <hi>Sabbath</hi> is within in our hearts; tranquilitie of Conscience is our <hi>Sabbath.</hi> It seems in <hi>Augustines</hi> time, the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish, and the Christian Sabbath were both upon the same day; but the Jewes by their supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and loose observation, lose all the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and comfort of Gods day, burying all the life and spirit of it in their grosse and literall interpretations, not minding it as a day of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rest, ordained chiefly for spirituall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly reposals, and exercises, of praysings, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirings
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:178839:39"/> of God, holy rejoycings and feastings, (the <hi>Jewes,</hi> the old <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> fast, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the nature of a Sabbath) and calling the poore to Feast, Almes, Instructing, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chising our Families, Wives, Children, Servants in the things of God, helping one another to remember what was taught, reasoning and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring together about the concernments of our soules, visiting the sick, &amp;c. Oh that we would all more mind holinesse in our relations and Callings; therein we honour <hi>Christ</hi> most visibly in the world, and hould out most of the glory of Religion, in expressing faithfulnesse, tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, forbearance, heavenly mindednesse, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, &amp;c. in our Families, and dayly conversings among men. This then is not to reduce us back to <hi>Judaisme,</hi> but to the practise of an Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the first and most ancient; then we <hi>Judaise</hi> when we rest in the bare letter of the Law as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, which <hi>Christ</hi> reproves, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.20, 21. we are bound to the letter of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, fourth, ninth, tenth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as much as ever the Jews were: but we must goe further, and turne the Letter into the Spirit. This the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Article 17. doth assert, saying, No Christian man whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:178839:39"/> is free from the obedience of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, which are called Morall: By the Law Morall we understand all the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements taken in their full extent, and so the fourth Commandment as well as any other; we play the Christians, not by destroying the Letter, but by fulfilling the Letter in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. There is a double Antichrist which we are to be aware of, a Litterall Antichrist that would destroy the Spirit; and a Spirituall Antichrist that would destroy the letter of the Scriptures; the Spirit is wrapt up in the Letter, and the Letter must be resolved into the Spirit, and we must not seperate between the Word and the Spirit. <hi>Jewish Sabbath</hi> sounds harsh; but it hath been the constant subtilty of the Serpent, to disguise Truths with names. The Jewes had great Priviledges; Salvation is of the Jewes, <hi>John</hi> 4.22. the giving of the Law, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises; to them were committed the Oracles of God; of them came <hi>Christ,</hi> according to the Flesh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. &amp; 9.4.5. how ever blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is happened to them, untill the fulnesse of the Gentiles be come in; yet their comming in shall be the glory and riches of the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12.25. they are a people of great
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:178839:40"/> Promises, and great Priviledges; it may be the Lord may one day inquire and take notice what usage they have had among the Nations. Nor can this practise of the <hi>Sab ath</hi> be righteously taxed, to have any affinity with loose, unsound opinions; as of the Libertines, who say, That God is the Author of sinne simply, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsecally the sinner; and that they may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any sinne, and need not to be humbled or troubled for it. Many subtle disputes there are among the Schoolemen, about Gods condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall will, and his absolute will, and his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and his will. Can we span the Heavens? or can the Nutshell containe the Ocean? no more can our shallownesse comprehend of an infinite God, who is <hi>Ʋnus actus simplicissimus.</hi> All descriptions doe but darken him, besides what he speaks of himselfe, that blessed Three, Father, Sonne, and holy Spirit, incomprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in glory and grace coequall. That of <hi>Paul</hi> is enough to silence all the disputes of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.17.18.19.20.21.22.23. True, he holily wills, and wisely orders all the acts of the creature (as the Potter doth the Clay to make what he will of it) to his own glory, in the vessels of mercy, and the vessels of wrath,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:178839:40"/> so made and prepared for those ends and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, but twice cursed spirits, that from any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of Gods blessed providence, prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stination desperately take liberty to sinne, or to extenuate sinne; we must onely looke to Gods revealed will and word, and that tells us what we are to thinke of sinne, and shewes u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how every act of sinne, (especially in Saints) is against the heart of God, his holy nature, and his holy Law; grace is solely Gods worke in us, which we are to prayse him for, affliction is Gods will upon us, which we are to blesse him for; sinne is our will naturally, which we are to hate, to mourne for, to repent dayly in the sence of the pardon of it; its properly, I say, the creatures own worke, however God uses it as he did the malice of <hi>Judas,</hi> and the Devill, for high and glorious ends, <hi>John</hi> 13.27. <hi>Math.</hi> 4.1. As little a kinn is it to those other opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of free will, falling away from grace, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall redemption, being above Ordinances, which takes so many, who erre, not knowing the Scriptures, and the power of the Death and Resurrection of <hi>Christ</hi> in their own hearts. <hi>But this contradicts the Government and Law.</hi> Ans. No command or way of <hi>Christ</hi> can be charged
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:178839:41"/> to breed any inconvenience, or disturbance, to the government and peace of any Nation: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heathen persecuting States and Princes we owe subjection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. also Tribute, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, Feare, Honour, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.7. but nothing of our Consciences in matter of worship; they owe us Protection, and we must pay our debt of subjection, though they should deny theirs, and that even <hi>for Conscience sake,</hi> so the Apostle: but God hath raised us up in this Island, a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly supreame Magistracy, (God now having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided by the Sword the controversie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to whom the legislative power of these Nations doth belong, which did alwayes reside in the peoples delegates) a government, that is the mirror of the world for mercies, a standing monument of Gods power and protection, that countenances godlinesse, (a favour the Church hath enjoyed but very rarely, let us use this calme season well: we are apt to grow carnall wanton, effeminate, worldly, under liberty, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantini favor, venenum Ecclesiae</hi>) and in the face of the world and all dangers, have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all the Churches of Christ, and their liberties: witnesse that memorable Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 4. <hi>Martii, die Sabbathi,</hi> 1647. (concerning
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:178839:41"/> the <hi>Scotch</hi> Papers, who would have forced up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> us by a Covenant, principles of persecution) since that time, how hath God witnessed for them in so admirable and uninterupted a stream of successes and Victories? would they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with the Spirit of those Papers (Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over Consciences) they had not been expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to conflict with so many bloody tryalls; but they durst not meddle with that flower in <hi>Christs</hi> Crown, Power over Consciences. <hi>Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Government</hi> stands no need of <hi>Caesars</hi> Sword, and never sought to it to defend it against He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes, &amp;c. How fatall it hath been to States to make Acts about Religion,<note place="margin">Non coercet, sed provoca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> violentia.</note> all Hystories can witnesse, and <hi>England</hi> in an History of Blood. How short lived was the <hi>Covenant,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Childe of contention, contrary to the intention of the first contrivers, who were very godly and wise men: If God had not in his Wisedome otherwise ordered it, and taken the crafty in their own snare, it might have proved as bad as <hi>Circumcision</hi> to the <hi>Shechemites, Gen.</hi> 34.22.23.24.25.26. Their Christian mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and tendernesse, witnessed in their unparallel'd clemency towards, and forbearing of prejudiced dissenting Brethren, (especially
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:178839:42"/> those of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with more bitternesse and harshnesse inveighing, than becoms Ministers of the Gospel, which teaches subjection to Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) is presidentiall to all Common-wealthes. We have onely to blesse God for them, and the many miraculous deliverances they have had from Plots and Conspiracies hatched at home and abroad, in all Nations round about, during their sitting, and to mourne for their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which will accompany all Governments, till <hi>Christ</hi> come; between which, and all other Governments of men, that ever were, or shall be, there will be found a vast and eminent diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. <hi>But this will encourage others to propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and so we shall have no Sabbath. Answ.</hi> Men godly and consciencious, dare not act per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versly, or profanely. And though the Civill Magistrate hath no power to force Religious Practises upon Consciences; yet he may, and ought to restraine men from practising against the light of their Consciences, in such open acts of prophanesse, as are every where committed. and which godly hearts mourne for. If mens Consciences tell them its Gods day, let them keep it as a day to the Lord, not in idle walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Alehouse-hauntings. He that pretend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:178839:42"/> Conscience, (which is guided either by the light of Nature, or Scripture) in acts of grosse unnaturall wickednesses, as Swearing, Cursing, Oppression, Defaming, Duells, Adultery, Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennesse, Disobedience, Idlenesse, Promise-breakings, Lying, Couzening, Perjury, Stealing, Murther, Rebellion, &amp;c. he deserves the sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est blow of the Magistrates Sword, which must be a terror to evill works, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3.4. We are to blesse God for such, having formerly had those who did terrifie good works. It hath been the honour of the English Christians, that they have been the strictest observers of <hi>Sabbaths;</hi> and I am perswaded, the Kings Booke for sports, and recreations on Sundayes, pressed upon god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ministers to reade, (and did occasion the si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencing of many) contrary to their Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, did hasten the ruine of that Family. I should subscribe to that of <hi>Augustine,</hi> in <hi>Psal.</hi> 92. <hi>Melius est arare, quam saltare Die Sabbati:</hi> Its better to Plow, than to Play, or Pott on the <hi>Sabbath dayes. But than we shall keep two Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths. Answ. Paul</hi> would at one time comply for reasons of Brotherly love, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.1. &amp; 21.26. at another time he would not suffer it in <hi>Peter, Gal.</hi> 2.11.12.13.14. <hi>Daniel</hi> would be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:178839:43"/> obstinate in the profession of his Conscience in case of Persecution, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. Its certaine, nothing in Religion is indifferent, the least punctilio deserves to be maintained with the bloodyest Martyrdome. That may be lawfull to me, which may not be expedient, with respect to others. For feare of Persecution, we may not abate the least Ace of a practise; edifying opportunities, we may and should take hold of any day: In this case, grudge not God a little more time; its time gained. <hi>Many Judgements have befallen men on that day. Ans.</hi> As many on other dayes, if they had been as well observed. <hi>The Saints have had many refreshments in those dayes. Ans.</hi> So they have upon other dayes also. Our enjoyments are no Arguments to prove Ordinances, Scripture must doe that. A Word of Scripture is better than the Voice of an Angel, or the highest experiences of Saints: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Book of Common Prayer, and other corrupted administrations of Ordinances, had spirituall refreshments. In darke times, <hi>Christ</hi> will beare with much in the people, as he did with the Apostles before his Resurrection, which he would not afterwards, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.25. God would have us now to know his mind in every
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:178839:43"/> point of Worship more perfectly, not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by Custome or Tradition, as formerly, Antichrist did at first spring out of these, and mens cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity of those they had given up the guidance of their Consciences unto. <hi>But how shall we walke towards other Brethren that differ from us in judgement, or practise, in this or any other point. Ans.</hi> Not bitterly, or with harshnesse opposing, or as Masters of other mens Consciences, or as if we had some Patent for Infallibility, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing our judgements upon them, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 14. the whole Chapter layes down Rules) if they aske any thing, with meeknesse and humility to shew our judgements; yet so, as we may be mistaken, and as rather desiring to learne of them, at other times forbearing discourses about contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall points, being rather willing to conferre in Fundamentall and edifying Truths, as <hi>Christ</hi> with <hi>Nichodemus</hi> about Regeneration, Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Humiliation the first and maine worke of the soule, to see that that be layd right, <hi>John</hi> 3.3. or as <hi>Christ</hi> with the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> about our ignorance of <hi>Christ,</hi> our need of <hi>Christ,</hi> as water of life; <hi>Christs</hi> willingnesse to give himselfe to us, as he would doe water, the most ordinary thing, <hi>John</hi> 4.10. afterwards
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:178839:44"/>
               <hi>Christ</hi> instructs her in point of worship, <hi>ver.</hi> 21▪ 22.23.24. its praeposterous for men to be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous about Baptisme, Church-order, &amp;c. before they have a through worke of grace upon their hearts, a sure and sound foundation layd in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry within. First see the heart be Baptized in the blood of <hi>Christ,</hi> first get a true heart in the full assurance of Faith, sprinkled from an evill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; then bring the body to be washed in pure Water, the whole body, not a part, washed▪ not sprinkled, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. see first <hi>Christ</hi> the great Fundamentall Ordinance, the <hi>Alpha</hi> of all Ordinances, and the spirit the earnest of our Inheritance, the first Fundamentall grace, be first in the soule, else we are but intruders upon Ordinances. It will put all our graces much to it, to deale with prejudised Saints, that differ from us in judgement and practise, its hard to know how to converse with such, it will require much selfe-deniall, and moderation; <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> parted upon a lesser account, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.39. We know not what mines of Gunpowder lye in the hearts of the best, when we come to be touched and crossed; there will be great apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in such cases, to entertaine jealousies, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judises, slightings, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.3. thinke other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:178839:44"/> that differ, may have more grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> others for their Graces, not their opinions. Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion will not sanctifie. Of all sorts of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what desperate wretches? All opinions must yet shake, and grace onely will stand in the day of <hi>Christ.</hi> Be humbled as much for prejudices, as grosser corruptions, they are breaches of the Commandement of Love, and grievings of the spirit, by which we are sealed; goe to <hi>Christ</hi> upon the first risings of them, to subdue them; the more subject to such evills, be the more watchfull, the more in Prayer; if offence be given, give the first satisfaction; he is the strongest Christian, that can soonest yeild, that can see most grace and least infirmity in another; make a little grace much, much infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity little. Sweet Christian condescentions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get and nourish Love. Remember how <hi>Christ</hi> beares with us, crooked peeces; interpret all in love, and let that love be ingenuous, and of a Gospel-stampe, the same with <hi>Christs,</hi> not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit with sweetnesse of nature, cunning, or prudentiall considerations; take heed of whis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering, reporting; beleeve nothing that may foment jealousie; recompence failings, with loving carriages and visits; blesse God for any
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:178839:45"/> grace, be humbled for any infirmity you see<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> another, as if it were thine owne; reproo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> faithfully, and tenderly, as sensible of thy ow<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> failings; by grace thou stands, pitty and resto<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the fallen; Pray much in secret for others; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present one Saint sweetly to another; avoyd a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> reflections, inveighings; get new influences o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Love from <hi>Christ</hi> dayly, trust not to any grac<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> received to act thus. Finally, according to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Apostles Canon, <hi>Let all things be done in Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.14. he confutes a great error wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> strong arguments only, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.12. the prescrip<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions are common, but the practise not so. Ho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> sad to see the divisions of Saints, (Printing on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anothers infirmities, in stead of discoverin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truth, which we should looke upon onely in the light of the Scripture, without other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections) so many pieces up and downe? One, <hi>An Anatomy of Presbytery.</hi> Another, <hi>An Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy of Independency.</hi> Another, <hi>An Anatomy of Anabaptisme.</hi> Names, that men have forged, to signifie men that depend upon no Governmen<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> men twice Baptized, which these doe not own. It were a good step to Love, to lay downe al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Names of distinction, and to own whatsoever is good in all those wayes. He is too great in his
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:178839:45"/> owne opinion, that can comply with no Saints, but those of his own, and would tye all to his own, as if it were <hi>Josephs</hi> Sheafe, to which all other Sheaves must doe obeysance. We know the story of the Tyrant, that could make all men of one length, either by beheading, or racking. Thinke not, all beyond us, to be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest with a spirit of humour, and Haeresie, &amp;c. it may be Truth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. The <hi>Jews</hi> were the most rigide in their Religion, so stiffe for their <hi>Moses,</hi> for uniformity, they could not beare <hi>Christ,</hi> the Lord of glory, will not goe beyond <hi>Moses,</hi> would kill <hi>Christ</hi> as a discenter from them in judgement and practise, <hi>John</hi> 5.16.18. Set up Love, as the maine point, let it carry the chiefest stroake in Conscience; the Scripture makes it the chiefest grace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. Yea, God is Love, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8. Let not opinion get above Love, in which most of the spirit of the Gospel lies, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.23. Selfe-love, and selfe-esteeme, beget prejudice, all contrary to Love, which cannot dwell but in a heart emptied much of selfe. The Gospel doth not counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance surlinesse towards (suppose) opposers; but commands, <hi>with meekenesse to instruct such as oppose,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. I speake bewailing my own
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:178839:46"/> heart. To conclude this, since the Scriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houlds out but one <hi>Sabbath</hi> of holy rest, from six dayes labours, and that onely a seventh day <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, (Exod.</hi> 20.10. which God himselfe kept, whose resting that day is made the speciall ground &amp; reason of the command of sanctifying and keeping the seventh day, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.) and that a first <hi>Day-Sabbath</hi> is generally owned, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, as the living Child; let the Word of God (like <hi>Solomons</hi> Sword, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.24.) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the controversie in thy Conscience; onely doe all things in Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out judging others, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. not pleasing our selves, but our neighbour, to Edification, <hi>chap.</hi> 15.1.2. even as <hi>Christ, ver.</hi> 3.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
            <p>VVE have infinite reason to prize and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise this, and all holy Institutions of God, and of Christ, they are all very honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, no lesse then such as God and Christ hath practised: God Institutes the seventh day, and practised it first himselfe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. propounds himselfe a pattern to us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Christ</hi> also Institutes Baptisme, Supper, Preaching, (he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the first Gospel-Preacher, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.) Prayer,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:178839:46"/> Conference, and opening Scripture, Almes; and he practises every one of them himselfe, (in his own Person, and nothing but that among the Saints again can dissolve them) yea, some of them, after his Resurrection, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.15.27.38. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3. <hi>John</hi> 21.12.13. and shall we think our selves to be above all Ordinances? tremble at such thoughts, and learne obedience from such high Patterns: We cannot be too good for Ordinances, under our highest attainements, on this side of Heaven. <hi>Paul</hi> saw the Person of <hi>Christ,</hi> yet Baptized immediately by <hi>Ananias</hi> a Disciple, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.10. What God in his owne Person hath done before us, we may well doe, since he hath given us no worse worke to doe, than what he himselfe hath done when he was upon Earth, (and would doe againe) and shall the Disciple be better or wiser then the Master? <hi>Christ</hi> may say to us, as <hi>Abimelech</hi> to the People, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.48. <hi>What you see me</hi> (the Captaine of your salvation) <hi>doe, doe ye likewise:</hi> they who are above Ordinances, must be above <hi>Christ.</hi> What higher Patterne? what stronger Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can we have, than the example of God himselfe? We may say in this case, as they, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.71. <hi>What need we any further witnesse, we</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:178839:47"/>
               <hi>have heard it of his own mouth,</hi> and seen it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his own example; consider with what willingnes should we pay this holy Tribute of Time to the Lord; it is no ridged exaction to diminish any part of the sweetnesse and comfort of our time, no tyrannicall Imposition layd upon time; but the first fruits of Eternity, a giving us in hand some part of Heaven. God would have us aforehand, to inure our selves to an Heavenly state, and to know what our works shall be there where we shall have no more to doe with any thing of this world; God respected all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our good in it, the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was made for man; the very first Creation of it, was with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to mans good and benefit, to be a day of soule-sequestration from all converses below, and of being devoted to communion with God, and delightings in him. As <hi>Christ</hi> the great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance was made on purpose for mans salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; so all other lesser Ordinances were made for man also; in all of them, God eyed more (in some sence) our comfort, assurance, satisfaction, sanctification, than his own glory, (we are all the gainers) for what addition can be made to Gods infinite glory, by our best services, (which are but <hi>splendida peccata,</hi> in which is so much
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:178839:47"/> glistering drosse) then best, when worst and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>est in our owne eyes, which deceive us, with greatning our own imagined excellencies? That may be very Hell, which appears Heaven in our own and others eyes. There is a glorious Devill haunts our Duties; which onely the humble, watchfull Christian, can discover in his severall transfigurations. Consider againe, what a spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall obligation lyes upon us from this conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that God will take to himselfe a seventh part of our whole life to he consecrated to his service, as if he took pleasure in our worthlesse performances, the acceptation whereof, is one of the great miracles or his glorious unspeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Love: hereby we are bound to give God all our time, as his due, we owe it him all, and yet how little a share doe we put him off with, who gets lesse of our time, then God? all is too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for the world, for sinne, for pleasure; any little, we think enough for God; time is a more <hi>sacred</hi> thing, then the most think;<note place="margin">Ex hoc mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to pende eternitas.</note> its most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and least esteemed; few know what it means, till they come upon a Death-bed, and then they would give a thousand worlds for a little of that time they lavished and squandered away in sinne and vanity: men onely triflle in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:178839:48"/> serious things, and are serious in trifles. <hi>Give to</hi> Caesar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caesars, <hi>and to God the things that are Gods;</hi> time is Gods due, yea, the creame and flowre of our time, our youth, the the prime and strength of our dayes, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12. it all belongs to God, and its Sacriledge to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow it upon any, but him; to waste it in sinfull carnall pleasures, which all end in sorrow and anxiety of soule, and turn into gall and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, imbittering all thoughts of God, whom it should be sweet to us alwayes to thinke of. How many young men, and others, (tempting each other to sin) sport and idle away their time, and think it tedious &amp; slow, which hath the swiftest motion of any thing in the world, a moment of which cannot be recalled? O the wofull out-cryes upon Death-beds of the neglect of time, the vain expence of time! Those men commonly are not weary so much of any time, as of that which God hath more especially marked for his service; How weary would such be of Heaven? Their misery is, they cannot cease from sinne, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpius Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bathum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> 2.14. they have no <hi>Sabbath</hi> within in their hearts, and so they cannot tell how to spend a <hi>Sabbath:</hi> Most are ready to be snatched out of the world by death, before ever they
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:178839:48"/> consider, understand for what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the world, which was to be happy in enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing communion with God, depending on him living wholly to him, as having no jurisdiction of themselves, or being their own, but his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Every <hi>Creature</hi> we see lives and dyes to us,<note place="margin">Sic vos non vobis melli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatis apes.</note> we to the first uncreated being, God himselfe, Mans great end is taught in his first Creation, immediately after which, the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted, as if he were not made to stay here, but onely to stop out of this world to rest and eternity; our chiefest Interest lies in another world. The <hi>Sabbath</hi> was ordained for a more speciall day of speaking with God in the <hi>Mount,</hi> and that we might carry in our faces all the Weeke after the shinings of those blessed fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowships and converses with God: Observe what <hi>Sabbath-dayes</hi> frames of spirits we have, the same commonly runs through all our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments and duties all the Weeke after. God would have us to make his <hi>Sabbaths</hi> to be dayes of delight, <hi>Isay</hi> 58.13. he cannot endure we should thinke them burthens, that crosses the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of their Institution. Religion consists most in holy joy and delights; So <hi>David,</hi> he rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed more in Gods Word and Commandments,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:178839:49"/> than souldiers use to doe in the richest spoyle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their enemies, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.162. He danced before the Arke, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.14. with all the might of his joy. Let every day finde us with a Sabbath-dayes spirit, turning all things (Meat, Drinke, Cloathes, &amp;c.) into Ordinances, of seeing, and tasting, and enjoying Gods love. We should get extraordinary Heavenly frame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon the seventh day, and those should be ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and common with us all the six dayes after: We should keep fresh and alive every Divine touch we have had upon our hearts, by Faith, Prayer, Meditation of the Promises, and not los<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in our imployments any thing of our Heavenl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gettings. There should be little difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>Weeke-dayes,</hi> in regard o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the frames of our hearts. We should enjoy a dayly Baptisme, Supper, Sabbath, dayly have our hearts dipped in the blood of <hi>Christ,</hi> dayly feast upon the love and fulnesse of <hi>Christ,</hi> dayl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sabbathize and delight in God, as our onely rest and center. The Gospel requires of us a constant frame of Heavenlinesse, as if we we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> already come to the spirits of just men, mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perfect to the Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem, Heb.</hi> 12.23. Alas! sometimes how cleere every thought o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:178839:49"/>
               <hi>Christ</hi> takes, melts, breakes the heart? why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it not alwayes so? We are called the Temples of the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. in the Temple there were Prayses, Halluja's, Musicall Instruments, (it was the place of all Ordinances) continuall singings, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.33. typicall of our spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall frames. To sanctifie a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> is to rest and delight in God, as he delighted in <hi>Christ,</hi> and in us from all Eternity, rejoycing over us, even as a Bridegroome over the Bride, which is the highest joy, <hi>Isay</hi> 62.5. resting in his Love, joying over us with singing, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17. Our Coppy is set us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.10. to rest as God rested, and as <hi>Christ</hi> rested; God rejoyceth in all his works, <hi>Psal</hi> 104.31. he saw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. so should we rejoyce in all his works and dealings with us, seeing all good, praysing him in every dispensation, as holy <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 1.21. accounting all to come from his infinite Love, for all things are good that come from him, even those things which we call evill. So it is a <hi>Sabbath</hi> dayes worke to overlooke all Gods works of Creation and Providence, and triumph in them, <hi>Psal.</hi> 92.4. Looke above head and view all on each hand; What a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:178839:50"/> Firmament! what a pleasant Earth! Think what a mighty glorious God, that hath made all these with a Word of his Mouth. Let Sun, Moone, Starrs, Trees, Mountains, Rivers, &amp;c. be as so many plain Sermons of God. How can one look upon these, and not heare them Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing some Attribute of an infinite God. One saying, Behold a good God, God in me. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Behold a wise and powerfull God in me. Another, Behold a living God in me. Another, A full God, an unchangeable God, a free God in me, &amp;c. what a mighty rich God that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all these Creatures in their severall beings? what a gratious forbearing God that upholds the World, notwithstanding all the sinnes day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed against him in it? Its an injury done to the Creature, to see it, and looke upon it, and not see God in it. Thou losest the good and comfort of that Creature, that thou doth not behold the Art and Hand of the Maker in. So Meditate upon all Gods works, as to raise Meditation to a breaking out into an holy Triumphing in God and his Works, from a sight and sence of our Interest, Propriety in him, as to be able to say, <hi>All these are Gods, and that God is mine,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21.22.23. So likewise we are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:178839:50"/> to consider his wonderfull <hi>works</hi> of Providenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> over all the World, his admirable wise ordering of all things in reference to his Church and People: we should look to fill our hearts with holy wonderings, rejoycing at his great <hi>workes</hi> up and down the World, especially among us of this Nation (an Island of miracles, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the like not in the World againe) with whom he hath dealt in such an extraordinary way, no such glorious footsteps of his Power and Justice to be found any where else. What won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull appearings for us against our Enemies, in such a heape of Victories, (both by Land, and now lately by Sea, most remarkeable, therein giving us new earnests of continued protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) to the amazement of all the Nations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us? We should not lose a thread of any Providence, but gather them all together, and <hi>make</hi> Triumphs of them, and compose Songs to teach our Children. This we are taught in the 92. <hi>Psalme, ver.</hi> 4.5. a Psalme Penned on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose for the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, which consists of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Gods <hi>kindnesse, faithfulnesse</hi> in his diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent dealings in this World with the <hi>godly,</hi> and <hi>wicked,</hi> in such admirable straines of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, (and we of this Generation have seen as
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:178839:51"/> glorious as ever any did, all Nations combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, quarrelling against <hi>England,</hi> (the greatest part of it against it selfe) yet preserved) that we may sing with the Church <hi>Psal.</hi> 124. <hi>Psal.</hi> 118.10. Great reason we have yet further to trust God. Oh that those <hi>blacke markes</hi> may never be found on us or ours, <hi>They soone forgat his workes,</hi> Psal. 106.13. <hi>forgat God their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> ver. 21. <hi>Learned the workes of the Heathen,</hi> ver. 35. <hi>Were defiled with their own works,</hi> ver. 39. <hi>Envied</hi> Moses <hi>and</hi> Aaron, <hi>the Saint of the Lord,</hi> ver. 16. <hi>which provoked God to give them into the hand of those that hated them,</hi> ver. 41. <hi>But he remembred his Covenant,</hi> ver. 45. There is the ground of all his dealings with us. God looks upon <hi>Christ,</hi> sees in him infinite reason (in us he can see none) of doing all he doth. Eye Gods great beginnings among us of this Island; eye him in all his glorious motions, and stately Marchings through the Nations, and his high contestings with the Princely Families of the Earth, one after another, who have drunke of the Cup of Fornication and Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution with the Whore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. drunke with the blood of Saints and Martyrs of Jesus. It would be a peece of Heaven to live to see
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:178839:51"/> the great power of <hi>Christ,</hi> that hath conquere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> so many mighty Armies, triumphing spiritually in the hearts and lives of men. To see as great a change upon mans heart, as we have seen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Governments and affaires in the world. That is it we must pray for, a <hi>worke</hi> within, to answer the glorious <hi>worke</hi> of God among us without, that must set the Crowne upon all our, conquests and successes. He that sees not <hi>Christ</hi> within conquering his lusts with the scepter of his power, will never magnifie and blesse him for his conquests in the world. Its sad, to see carnality, formality, praejudices, and want of Love, creeping in upon the spirits of all sorts of men. <hi>Christ</hi> doth expect to reape other fruit, and we may expect that he will make good his promises, in powring out of the spirit upon all sorts. We shall see a day shortly of <hi>Christs</hi> making way to his glorious Kingdome through the spirits of men, more than we have seen of it in the bloods of men. VVhatsoever mis-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions may be among the Saints of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> in respect of present providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Ordinance, yet let us all conspire to excell one another in Love and Holinesse, and sweet condescentions, and consider if all provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:178839:52"/> doe not bespeake and prophesie a unity, and combination of hearts of Saints both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> Our <hi>Sabbath</hi> should be nothing but an Embleme, an imitation of our Sabbaticall rest, and eternall communion with God hereafter: The dayly consideration of which, will be a means of sanctifying us, and cheering us in the middest of all troubles and afflictions, with the hopes of that promised rest. <hi>Christ</hi> shall be our rest then, make him to be our rest now; let Faith be every day bringing him in with new glory and delight to the soule; he was Gods rest, and he must be ours; God and we have but one meeting-place, resting-place, namely, <hi>Christ;</hi> and we shall never finde rest, till we look upon our selves, as God looks upon us in <hi>Christ.</hi> No duties, performances, gifts, frames of spirit, injoyments, can be our rest; nothing but <hi>Christ,</hi> and him onely, singly. If we did value our selves (as we ought) by <hi>Christ,</hi> nothing should be able to hinder our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing. A Christians whole life must be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Sabbath,</hi> Rest, Reposall, Quietation in God. The same <hi>Sabbath</hi> must enter into us now, which we must one day enter into, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. Heaven is begun here, the same joyes in their
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:178839:52"/> measure, the same everlasting armes now em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing us, the same lips now kissing us, <hi>Song</hi> 1. 2. the same water of life being now free to us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. onely then we shall see, and drink more of the River it selfe, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. Blessed those that are Sabbatizing in <hi>Christ.</hi> No shakings of the Earth, no Alarmes of warr, &amp;c. shall afright or disturbe them in their Holy Requiems, <hi>Psal.</hi> 46.2.3. The pillars of the world may break, new troubles may arise, they shall not be moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Psal.</hi> 125.1. they <hi>keep a Sabbath</hi> that the world knows not of, and cannot <hi>keep,</hi> for there can be no <hi>Sabbath</hi> without <hi>Christ.</hi> Look princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally at the inward <hi>Sabbath.</hi> The invisible part of Religion is the chiefest, and the most essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall. All the outward part of it will be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, without an inward infinite <hi>worke</hi> upon the soule. Keep such a <hi>Sabbath</hi> as <hi>Christ</hi> doth in Heaven. Write as neer the Coppy as you can. Make <hi>Christ</hi> your constant, standing Ordinance at all times, in all places. And think not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the pompous part of Religion without the soule, which will weare out. The Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Sabbath</hi> consists in our dying to all things within us, and without us, besides <hi>Christ;</hi> In ceasing from our own wisedome, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.4.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:178839:53"/> and in ceasing from man, <hi>Isay</hi> 1.16. in ceasing from sinne (which is the soules tumult, disorder, disquiet, as well as pollution) and living to the will of God, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4.1.2. As Christ was Crucified the sixth day, immediately before the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> so must we be crucified to all comforts and enjoyments, before we can come to a <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> of rest and delight in Christ: we should be preparing continually to enter upon our <hi>Sabbath</hi> of Death, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13) so live as you would have death, yea <hi>Christ</hi> to finde you. <hi>Christ</hi> must be our example, how to live, and how to dye, that we may be able to say with him, <hi>John</hi> 19.30. <hi>It is Finished. John</hi> 17.4. <hi>I have Fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the worke,</hi> &amp;c. So thou, I see all is done, concluded, and perfected; all scores cleered in the righteousnesse and satisfaction, and death of <hi>Christ.</hi> And with <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6.7.8. <hi>I have finished my course, I have fought a good Fight,</hi> and seen sinne slaine and dye before me; I have nothing more to doe, onely to receive <hi>my Crown. I am now ready for to be offered up, and so dye,</hi> (as it were) in Christs lap singing. In times of sicknesse, there will be no rest in the flesh, we had need see to have rest in the spirit afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand. How sweetly and quietly may he goe to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:178839:53"/> his rest, that hath done his <hi>Dayes-worke,</hi> been diligent in striving against sinne (which is to overcome sinne) in observing <hi>Christ</hi> in every ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation; in keeping up alwayes the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vigour of his graces, losing nothing of any Income, in improving all seasons and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the utmost to get from <hi>Christ,</hi> and to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due sinne, forgetting things behind, reaching forth, and pressing forward toward the <hi>Marke,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12? How sweet will our <hi>Sabbath</hi> be after all our toylings and moylings in this world? How sweet our rest, sleep in the dust, after our hard labour?<note place="margin">Optimum Naturae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum mors, <hi>Sen.</hi>
               </note> How soft a Bed the Grave, <hi>Isay</hi> 57.2. after a weary Pilgrimage? How sweet our retirement to Heaven, and all those prepared Mansions of glory, (<hi>John</hi> 14.2.) after our wearisome abode upon Earth, as a place full of the habitations of cruelty and oppression, <hi>Psal.</hi> 74.20? It may be God will not have us to dye Rich and Honourable in the world; but he would have us dye Holy, Rich in good <hi>Workes,</hi> full of the fruits of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and the first fruits of Eternity, and so goe to Heaven Praysing, and in all the Triumphs of Faith. Death cannot look unfriendly gastlily upon him, who hath lived in continuall famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:178839:54"/> with God, under the dayly appearings of a God, and streamings out of the blood of <hi>Christ</hi> upon his Conscience, to the washing thereof. We should hasten to get to our full stature in Christ, and be ever in a posture for Heaven, (there being but one step between us and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) so will death be made a holy desireable Ordinance of rest and communion with God. So it was to <hi>Christ, Luke</hi> 12.50. he was pained with his Love, to dye for us. His Death was as a Baptisme; he had such a desire as Saints have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any Ordinance. We shall finde it far better to be with <hi>Christ,</hi> then to be among the best Saints in the best Ordinances, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. yet, how much Heaven in the communion of Saints, nay oft in the society of one poore Saint in conference and prayer? The face of a Saint (whatsoever Judgement he be of) is lovely and delightfull. he speaks the Language of Paradise, he hath within in his soule an Eccho of Heaven, in his heart the habitation of God, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.17. What blessed Ordinances are those (as also clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sett Communions) of which our hearts are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to say, as <hi>Peter</hi> upon the <hi>Mount, Let us build Tabernacles here, it is good for us to be here.</hi> Theres a glorious generall <hi>Sabbath</hi> comming,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:178839:54"/> (<hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. that shall put downe all before it) when all the Saints shall be together with <hi>Christ,</hi> at that last great Supper of the Lambe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.9. Not a word then of any difference of judgement, nothing but perfect harmony of soules in the praysings of Christ, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.11. &amp; 19.6.7. and loving each other. Our <hi>Sabbath</hi> should resemble that. This standing seventh day, is an holy symbole of that (praefigured in the <hi>Sabbath</hi> of yeares, and in the great <hi>Sabbath</hi> of years, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.4.5.8.10. now abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16.) that great Jubilee shall be the period of all Monarchies, Governments, Administrations, Ordinances; that shall be a <hi>Sabbath</hi> of Jubilee even to the very creatures also, now groaning (as under pressure of the usage and usurpation of wicked men) and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling in paine, dayly and hourely waiting with earnest expectation, for the manifestation of the Sonnes of God, to be delivered from bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19.20.21.22. Than shall the present groanings of the Creature be turned into singings. The Heavens shall be glad, and the Earth rejoyce, and the Trees of the Wood shall sing out at the presence of the Lord, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 16.31.32.33. The Mountains and the Forrest
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:178839:55"/> shall breake out into singing, because th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord shall glorifie himselfe in <hi>Israel, Isay</hi> 44.23. The Fir-tree shall rejoyce, and the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> because the Lord hath broken the staffe of the wicked, and the scepter of the rulers, <hi>Isay</hi> 14.5.7.8. The Mountains shall breake forth into singing, because the Lord shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his afflicted, <hi>Isay</hi> 49.13. All the Creation shall be turned (as it were) into melody and Musicke, and holy Festivity, like a multitude keeping Holy-day, <hi>Psal.</hi> 42.4. having their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-day cloathes on, and appearing in their resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution-robes, (to rejoyce with the Saints, those Children of the Resurrection, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.36. the Citizens of the new <hi>Jerusalem, Rev.</hi> 22.1.2. (in which shall be no wicked men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14.15. <hi>Isay</hi> 35.9.10. who shall not be able to endure the presence of <hi>Christ</hi> there, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.35.) of which the New Testament Churches are, and should be Types, yea the Scripture oft calls the Church, the Kingdom of Heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause none should come there, or be admitted to Ordinances of Membership, (Baptisme and Supper) but such as (in the judgement of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) are fit to goe to Heaven immediately) the Mountains shall skip like Rammes, and the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:178839:55"/> little Hills like Lambs, <hi>Psal.</hi> 114.4. as men d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of long Captivity, daunce for joy, all the Creature shall be full of solemnity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing that it is come into the hand of <hi>Christ,</hi> (the sole absolute Heire of all things, by whom and for whom, they were all made and created, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16.17, 18.) and of the Saints, for whose sake all things are, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. Yea, and we our selves also, which have the first fruits of the Spirit; even we our selves grone within our selves, waiting for the adoption, the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our bodies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. This second <hi>Adams Sabbath,</hi> shall farr exceed in glory the first <hi>Adams Sabbath</hi> in Paradise, it shall restore all that he lost with manifold additions. We doe not so well know at present what to make of Heaven, and the Kingdom of <hi>Christ,</hi> (we speak like poore babes and sucklings, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11.) onely by some certaine sweet tasts and praeliba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it in those first fruits, we may more then guesse, it is a state that will drowne us all in the height and depth of its glory: we shall perfectly know it, when we come into it, then shall that which is in part be done away, when that which is perfect is come, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10. then we shall raigne with him in soules and bodies,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:178839:56"/>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. (our vile bodies being changed and fashioned like his glorious body, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.) in that Kingdome which he hath prepared and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, for the manifestation of his glory, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.10. in his poor tempted afflicted Saints, who then shall feast with him, after all the hard fare they have had in the world, <hi>Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 22.28.29.30. they shall be no losers in the conclusion, Heaven will make up all, <hi>For a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of afflicton, they shall have an eternall weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. yea, all our present affli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctions, temptations, sicknesses, necessities, deaths, are so sweetned and sanctified unto us, that they are but preparatives for, and introduction into, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.36.) if not parcels of that glory of the Kingdom of <hi>Christ,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13.) Than there shall be no more sin, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3. No more Death, <hi>cap.</hi> 21.4. No more Teares, <hi>cap.</hi> 7.17. No more Devill to molest, or buffet us with any temptation, <hi>cap.</hi> 20.2.3. but we shall see <hi>Christ,</hi> and serve him, and raigne with him for ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3.4.5. That shall be our day of joy with <hi>Christ, Mat.</hi> 25.21. our time of eternall refreshing with <hi>Christ,</hi> after all the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and sorrowfull steps we have gone in this world, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. our <hi>Sabbath</hi> of everlasting
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:178839:56"/> rest (to us troubled ones) with all the Saints, when the Lord Jesus shall be revealed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with his mighty Angels, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.7. The Angelicall Ministery shall then cease, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. We shal have no need, as now, of being served by Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Christ</hi> alone shall be the Saints visible Ordinance, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.22. and he shal rule and raigne as the head of the Church, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.21.22. and of all Principalities, Mights, and Dominions, having put downe all Rule, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power, and having all his enemie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under his feet, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.25. Afterwards, (that long day of Gods Judging the world by the Man Jesus being ended, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>John</hi> 5.21.22.) <hi>Christs</hi> Mediatoriall, or Ministeriall Kingdom shall cease, (but the glory and honour of it, (as the Lambe that was slain, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13.) he shall retaine for ever in the eyes of all the Saints in the fullest glory) and then shall the Sonne himselfe also be subject unto him that put all things under him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.27. The Fathers Love, was the originall and source of all the acts of <hi>Christs</hi> Mediatorship, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. and they shall all end in him, and God <hi>shall be all in all,</hi> all our life and happinesse, and that immediately; which shall be the utmost, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:178839:57"/> highest degree of glory, beyond which there<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> no degree, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. How should we groan<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to have this opposite life of sinne and selfe, al<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> destroyed, and to be swallowed up in that life<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of God (blessed for ever, Father, Word, and<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> holy Spirit, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7.) which is now begui<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in us (<hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.) by<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his blessed Spirit, and shall then be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected (<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49.) in our soule<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and bodies together, so shall we ever be wit<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Lord, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.17? To the onely wise Go<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> our Saviour, be Glory and Majesty, Dominio<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and Power, now and ever, Amen. <hi>Jude</hi> 25.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>FOl. <hi>18.</hi> line <hi>23.</hi> reade Diei. f. <hi>65.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> r. <hi>1</hi> Chron<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>9.33.</hi> f. <hi>101.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> r. mens hearts, &amp;c. Other fault<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and mistakes, pardon and correct with Christian Love. Read<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with the Bible in one hand. Judge what you will of the Opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion; let love have the praedominancy in the Conscience▪ <hi>1 Cor. 13.13.</hi> And though there be difference about som<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> commands of the Old Testament, let all professing Saintship<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> agree in those Two great and positive commands of the Ne<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Testament, To Beleeve, and Love, <hi>1 John 3.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I beleeved, therefore have I spoken, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>4.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>IV. Moneth 1652.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:178839:57"/>
            <p>A Word more to that consideration (the constant Practise of all Churches for so many Ages) which hath no small prevalency upon the Consciences of men. For the first two or three hundred years after Christ, Infant Baptisme, and the first day Sabbath, will be hardly found, either in the Opinion or Practise of those purer Times. Writers are oft brought in, speaking on all sides. We must onely heare Christ, (the great Prophet of the Church) and the Apostles, and nothing else must have influence upon our Conscience. It will not be demanded of us at the last day, whether we held and beleeved, as the Church beleeved; but what warrant we had from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to guide our Consciences. The Church is the Spouse of Christ, must be in subjection to her Head and Lord; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the Scriptures Supremacy and infallibility onely. The consideration of the practise of Churches generally, should impose a holy feare and suspition upon our hearts, and cause great circumspection and watchfulnesse, and to see that which we professe against, be overcome with the mighty cleerenesse and brightnesse of Scripture, shining in upon Conscience. What is Catholicke (generally, constantly practized) hath a great force of binding Consciences. The world knows this by experience. For how long a tract of time did a read Liturgy, Lordly Episcopacy, &amp;c. continue in the Church? and the very name of Antiquity, Universality, &amp;c. begets a naturall reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the Consciences of men not perfectly subjugated to the Authority of Scriptures, which onely must, and can satisfie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in all its scruples; and besides that blessed umpire, there is nothing can lay any just claime to infallibility, no not the Canons and Constitutions (suppose) of Angels. Matters of long usage, may be allowed their Honourable Sepultures, as the the Temple and <hi>Jewish</hi> Ceremonies had after Christs Death, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.17. but once the word of God discover things to my Conscience, not comprized within the rule of Faith, I cannot
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:178839:58"/> than allow them a moment longer intertainment there. Yet must all the Methods of the Gospel be observed in laying them downe, having all respect to peace and edification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. not to be over-zealous for a Truth, so as to despise another Brother dissenting, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.10. so charitably to walke, (not grieving, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending a Brother) as my good may not be evill spoken of, <hi>ver.</hi> 15.16.22. preferring alwayes holinesse and peace, and the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my neighbour, before any Opinion, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. &amp; <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.2. Neither is every dissent to be accounted a Schisme, (though we are not ignorant of Satans wiles in heightning dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of Saints to prejudices and breaches) which in some cases may be necessary; as in our departure from the <hi>Romis<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Church, and other corrupt Assemblies, wherein men make a Schisme from the Word of God. But when Churches doe consist of Gospel matter, Saints called, &amp;c. (among whom al<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Rules of Christian forbearance are duely and justly observed not looking so much what others hold, as how they hold it, on<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not imposing upon, but with meeknesse instructing another, &amp;c.) from such holy communities and Societies, no Schisme ought to be made notwithstanding any diversity of judgement amon<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> them, and to such fellowships of Saints combined to mutua<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Edification, Exhortation, Love, Watching, &amp;c. all Saints ought to joyne themselves, without delay. Onely I would caution what we call Schisme and Heresie, the world hath been too free in bestowing those names and titles, and its in vaine to hope to satisfie them; neither <hi>Johns</hi> mourning, nor <hi>Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> piping could content the <hi>Jewes.</hi> They are pleased with nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, cry up <hi>Moses, Moses,</hi> as if <hi>Christ</hi> were an enemy to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses,</hi> a secret underminer of their Government and Custome<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>John</hi> 5.85. and 11.48. They finde fault (like prejudiced Spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits) with every thing Christ doth, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.16.17.18.19. bu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> strict and rigide in the observation of their Customes, a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Traditions, preferring them before Christ, <hi>Math.</hi> 15.2.<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:178839:58"/>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 6.14. and 16.20.21. Though we should see Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> goe with never so few followers, and attendants at her backe; yet it is as noble and honourable, as if she had Princes and Kings to be her Lacqueyes. We are apt to looke at men and multitude, to see who, and how many goe before us. Its probable one may erre. Its possible many may erre. The Devil hath fixed particular mens names <hi>(Lutherans, Calvinists, Brownists)</hi> to Truths, to render them suspected of being onely the birthes of particular mens fancies. Look not at men, but things. The Light is not the worse, because the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticks but Clay. Its dangerous to have the Faith of our Lord Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of Glory, with respect of Persons, <hi>James</hi> 2.1. either over-valuing mens Persons, as they, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.11.12.13. or under-valuing them, who really move in a higher sphaere of knowledge of, and communion with Christ, than our selves. When the Person gives esteeme to the Truth, we doe not receive it as truth, simply considered, and in its owne light and authority. That is onely made Truth to me, or thee, which we take out of the very ballance of Scripture, after weighing, Praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be true to every practise, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve order and time, <hi>Math.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.2. View every Truth as it lyes in Scripture, and follow it with the same spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit it was writ with at first; being as zealously affected to Love, as to Truth. And though we cannot look for any absolute Unity and Perfection among Saints, in this present state of weaknesse; yet, I think, we may safely affirme, that it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (since the will of Christ is so) to be in a Church of Saints the weakest, and most labouring with infirmities, (for the exercise of Love, and forbearance one towards another, wherein is more obedience and selfe-deniall, than in the strictest exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Duties and Gifts, wherein may be much hypocrisie) than to converse visibly with Angels and Spirits of just men made perfect. I Pray for others, and my selfe, to be equally
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:178839:59"/> fearefull of Error, and faithfull to Truth, respecting tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> most which Christ respects most, as most resembling him, Love, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8. <hi>Not being censorious,</hi> Rom. 14.4. 1 Cor. 4.7. <hi>But esteeming others better then our selves,</hi> Phil. 2.3. <hi>Loving all Saints for Christs</hi> Image, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. <hi>Yea, and our very Enemies, Persecutors, Oppressors, for Christs</hi> command, Math. 5.44.45. Rom. 12.20. <hi>which is more then all</hi> Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, 1 Sam. 15.22. Math. 9.13.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <list>
               <item>VVHo can understand his errours? cleanse thou me from secret faults. <hi>Psal. 19.12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thou hast commanded us to keep thy precepts diligently, <hi>Ps.. 119.4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>O that my wayes were directed to keep thy Statues! <hi>ver. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Then shall I not be ashamed, when I have respect unto all thy Commandements. <hi>ver. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Open thou mine eyes, that I may behold wondrous things out o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thy Law. <hi>ver. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>I am a stranger on the Earth, hide not thy Commandement from me. <hi>ver. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thy testimonies also are my delight, and my Counsellers. <hi>ver. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>I made haste, and delayed not to keep thy Commandements. <hi>V. 60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Let my heart be sound in thy Statutes, that I be not ashamed. <hi>V. 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>I have seen an end of all perfection, but thy Commandement i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> exceeding broad. <hi>Ver. 96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How sweet are thy words unto my taste! yea, sweeter then hon<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to my mouth. <hi>Ver. 103.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Depart from me, ye evill doers: for I will keep the Commande<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of my God. <hi>Ver. 115</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:178839:59"/>
               <item>Hold thou me up and <hi>I</hi> shall be safe, and <hi>I</hi> will have respect unto thy Statutes continually. <hi>Ver. 117.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Order my steps in thy word: and let not any iniquity have Dominion over me. <hi>Ver. 133.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Make thy face to shine upon thy servant, and teach me thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. <hi>Ver. 135.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Leade me in thy truth, and teach me: for thou art the God of my salvation, on thee doe I wait all the day. <hi>Psal. 25.4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The meek will he guide in judgement, and the meek will he teach his way. <hi>Ver. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Behold thou desirest truth in the inward parts: and in the hidden part thou shalt make me to know Wisedome. <hi>Psal. 51.6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Purge me with Hysope, and <hi>I</hi> shall be cleane: wash me, and <hi>I</hi> shall be whiter then Snow. <hi>Ver. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Create in me a cleane heart, O God: and renew a right spirit within me. <hi>Psal. 51.101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Restore unto me the joy of thy salvation, and uphold me with thy free Spirit. <hi>Ver. 12.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <list>
               <item>GReat peace have they that love thy Law, and nothing shall offend them. <hi>Psal. 119.165.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Blessed are the undefiled in the way, <hi>Psal. 119.1. In</hi> whose heart is the Law of his God. <hi>Psal. 37.31.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it their Hearts, and I will be their God, and they shall be my People, <hi>Jer. 31.33. Heb. 8.10. Heb. 10.16.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:178839:60"/>
            <list>
               <item>THinke oft seriously of such places as these, till you feele Milke and Honey come out, which the Scripture yeilds abundantly, when drawne by the Spirit: make every Scripture thine owne, by <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Meditation,</hi> and Prayer.</item>
               <item>Blessed is the man whom thou chastenest, and teachest him in thy Law, that thou mayst give him rest in the dayes of adversity. <hi>Psal. 94.12.13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aske for the old pathes, where is the good way, and walke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ye shall finde rest to your Soules. <hi>Jer. 6.16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Let us therefore feare, lest a promise being left us of entring into his rest, any of you should seem to come short of it, <hi>Heb. 4.1.</hi> Promises spiritually applyed, will beget <hi>Holy Feare</hi> in us, and that will keep us from carnall security and presumption on one hand, as well as despaire on the other; both which arise out of false rests. See what your soules resting place is. The Dove found no rest for the sole of her foot, but the Ark. Not so the Raven. <hi>Gen. 8.9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>We which have beleeved doe enter into rest, <hi>Heb. 4.3.</hi> Faith brings to present possession of Christ, our rest: it makes every thing of Heaven reall, and as it were in hand.</item>
               <item>The wicked are like the troubled Sea, when it cannot rest, whose waters cast up mire and dirt. <hi>Isay 57.20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They have gone from mountaine to hill, they have forgotten their resting place, <hi>Jer. 50.6.</hi> Try every mountaine, goe where you will, you will finde no resting place for your hearts, till you lay them in Christs bosome. Say to thy soule, as <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omy</hi> to <hi>Ruth, Ruth 3.1.</hi> Shall I not seek rest for thee <hi>(my poore Soule)</hi> that it may be well with thee in the latter end. Shall I seeke so much for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, so much for Wife and Children, and neglect thee, who should be dearer to me than all? Say concerning all things below Christ, Arise yee and depart, for this is not your rest, because it is pollu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, it shall destroy you with a sore destruction, <hi>Micah 2.10.</hi> Whatsoever we place our rest in, besides Christ; it will one da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> most sorely destroy and disquiet, as the greatest sinne and pollution
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:178839:60"/> when you are in the middest of all enjoyments round about you, say, You are not yet come to your rest, <hi>Deut. 12.9. I</hi> cannot rest in any of these, miserable rests are they all. None of these shall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie or content me, onely Christ shall doe that. Such a soule is onely for Christs delight.</item>
               <item>Where is the place of my rest? saith the Lord, to him will <hi>I</hi> looke, that is poore and of a contrite spirit, and trembleth at my Word, <hi>Isay 66.1.2.</hi> A broken heart will make God onely its rest, and God will rest in it as his Heaven. God is its joy, and its Gods. A tender heart, checking and mourning for the least <hi>sin,</hi> and submitting unto, intertaining the least <hi>Truth,</hi> is of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest in Heaven, <hi>Psal. 51.17.</hi> Try what lyes underneath the soule, as its rocke, <hi>Psal. 73.26.</hi> Looke to your rest, its a short and sure way, by which we may know what our heart, and what our Heaven is made of: Every thing will tend towards, and long to be at its rest and center.</item>
               <item>I will give thee rest, <hi>Exod. 33.14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>I will give you rest, <hi>(Math. 11.28.)</hi> such as cannot be had any where in the world besides, <hi>(John 14.27.)</hi> which passes all understanding, <hi>(Phil. 4.11.)</hi> which none knowes, but he that hath it, <hi>Rev. 2.17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This is the rest wherewith yee may cause the weary to rest, and this is the refreshing. <hi>Isay 28.12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He shall enter into peace: they shall rest in their beds, each one walking in his uprightnesse, <hi>Isay 57.2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Blessed are the dead which dye in the Lord, they rest from their labours, and their workes follow them, <hi>Rev. 14.13.</hi> Doe no worke but what you would be willing should follow you to the grave, and meet you at the day of Judgement. Nothing but what is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> worke of God upon the soule will hould then, and such a <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> never faile.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iven rest unto his people: there <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> promise, <hi>1 Kings 8.56.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>